<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Beames of eternal brightness, or, Branches of everlasting blessings springing forth of the stock of salvation, to be spread over India and all nations of the earth, to the uniting all mankind as one single and simple body of everlasting love and peace in the original glory and creator of all things / written by a member of truth, John, who is called a Quaker.</title>
            <author>J. P. (John Perrot), d. 1671?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2898</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13177829</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13177829</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98353</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98353)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 433:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Beames of eternal brightness, or, Branches of everlasting blessings springing forth of the stock of salvation, to be spread over India and all nations of the earth, to the uniting all mankind as one single and simple body of everlasting love and peace in the original glory and creator of all things / written by a member of truth, John, who is called a Quaker.</title>
                  <author>J. P. (John Perrot), d. 1671?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Perrot. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>In this edition the imprint is printed as three lines.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Concord --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98353:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>BEAMES OF Eternal Brightneſs, OR, BRANCHES OF Everlaſting Bleſsings; Springing forth of the Stock of Salvation, to be ſpread over <hi>INDIA,</hi> and all Nations of the Earth, To the Uniting all Mankind, as one <hi>ſingle</hi> and <hi>ſimple Body</hi> of <hi>Everlaſting Love</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> in the Original Glory and Creator of all things.</p>
            <p>Written by a Member of Truth, <hi>JOHN,</hi> Who is called a <hi>QUAKER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black-ſpread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmil,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98353:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98353:2"/>
            <head>Beams of Eternal Brightneſs, <hi>or,</hi> Branches of Everlaſting Bleſſings, ſpringing forth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>O All ye <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>INDIA,</hi> and the reſt upon the face of the whole Earth, I can in no better way and manner ſalute you, than in this of the Bleſſing and Counſel of <hi>Eternal Life,</hi> In which you may come <hi>lively</hi> and <hi>joyfully</hi> to know the <hi>true Power</hi> which hath created all things, and ruleth and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneth all things according to his own Will and Pleaſure; who by Name, ſo as to be diſtinguiſhed (in every man's underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) from every other thing, is called <hi>The Searcher through all Darkneſs,</hi> or, <hi>The glorious Sun of the Soul,</hi> or, <hi>The Wonderful Power,</hi> or, <hi>The Incomprehenſible Wiſdom,</hi> or, <hi>The Immutable Holineſs,</hi> or, The <hi>from Eternity to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;</hi> becauſe theſe glorious Qualities are only proper to his infinite wonderful <hi>Eſſence,</hi> as unſpeakably more are, which I neither do nor can here mention.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> which I ſpeak of, who in Himſelf is infinitely <hi>more than all things;</hi> by whoſe <hi>Word <hi>all things were created in the beginning,</hi>
               </hi> and is a <hi>Being</hi> inviſible to every fleſhly thing, of whom <hi>divers Nations</hi> do hold <hi>divers Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> and ſo do make him in their Imaginations like unto <hi>divers things,</hi> and accordingly do worſhip in <hi>divers manners</hi> and <hi>wayes:</hi> but he being <hi>but one</hi> who created <hi>all things,</hi> and not likened un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>any thing</hi> that man makes, is only known aright, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped aright in one living, pure, and holy way. For which cauſe <hi>I hereby greet <hi>all the Indians,</hi> together with <hi>all Mankind</hi> upon the face of the Earth,</hi> in the feeling of that Power, Wiſdom and Life of Glory, which is able to reduce them all unto the true knowledge of himſelf, to the end that they may all become but of <hi>one heart, mind</hi> and <hi>ſoul</hi> for ever, worſhipping according to the <hi>true knowledge</hi> and <hi>pure underſtanding</hi> of him through an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal feeling, ſeeing, and perceiving him ariſing and appearing in his Power, Wiſdom and Glory in all their <hi>inward parts:</hi> So
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98353:3"/>
that when all men in all Nations, Countries and Lands ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the <hi>true knowledge</hi> of <hi>the Life, Power, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of their Maker and Creator <hi>in themſelves;</hi> then they ſhall have no need of any other inſtruction (touching the knowledge of their Maker) <hi>without them;</hi> and ſo knowing their Creator appearing <hi>in themſelves,</hi> will alſo know from him, (who ſo appeareth) the true and living way, of his true, living and pure Worſhip, which he teacheth all in the Unity and Truth of his own Wiſdom and Knowledge, the which muſt certainly put an end unto all that which is <hi>diverſe</hi> &amp; from the way of his <hi>own Life,</hi> and <hi>pure Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the Nature of man is contrary to the Nature of the Glorious Sun of the Soul, I hold it neceſſary to ſhew <hi>what the Nature of the <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other</hi>
               </hi> is, that as they are in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety, the <hi>worſt</hi> may be <hi>forſaken,</hi> and the <hi>beſt</hi> cleaved and adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto, and for ever <hi>loved</hi> and <hi>lived</hi> in, in the Power, Wiſdom and Glory thereof.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Nature of the Glorious Sun of the Soul, which was before the outward Sun was, is <hi>pure, holy, clean, undefiled</hi> and <hi>full of all Light and Vertue,</hi> even of all which ſtands in an Eternal Life;</hi> as alſo in it is the vertue, <hi>of reducing all things unto nothing again, as by it all things of nothing were</hi> (in the beginning) <hi>made and created.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>But the Nature of man is <hi>evil, corrupt, unclean, bruitiſh,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>full of darkneſs</hi> and <hi>ignorance <hi>of the true knowledge of the Power of Eternal Life.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Now if it be demanded, <hi>How</hi> and <hi>where <hi>the one</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>the other <hi>is to be rightly understood and known?</hi>
               </hi> To it I am free to anſwer thus; ſhewing introductionally,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Introd. </seg>
               </label> That the Soul of man <hi>is the ſenſible living part, that hath its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the body of fleſh, or humane tabernacle, whilſt the perceivance of breath is left therein, whereby man hath the ſenſe and feeling of <hi>joys</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>pains, pleaſures</hi> and <hi>ſorrows,</hi> &amp;c. To which <hi>inward part</hi> in all mankind I ſpeak of the Sun of the Soul, teſtifying, That the Light thereof <hi>in every ſoul,</hi> is of ſuch a <hi>purity</hi> and <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> ſhining in the <hi>inward parts</hi> of the <hi>Intelect</hi> or ſecret under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of man, that it hath <hi>no unity</hi> nor <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with his <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs</hi> and <hi>beaſtlineſs;</hi> ſhewing him, when no fleſh doth ſpeak unto him, that he having a rational ſoul put into him, ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98353:3"/>
not be like unto the beaſts of the field (which have not received that faculty) in his loathſom <hi>acts of defilement,</hi> and that he ſhould not in other caſes be worſe than the beaſts of the field (which onely <hi>eat</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> to their ſatisfaction, and having ſo done, when reſt is needful, do lie down in quietneſs, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of miſchief; and which in their mute ſtate, have not a mind of the vent of <hi>Execrations, Curſes, Oathes, Blaſphemies, Lying, Cheating, Stealing, Murdering,</hi> or the like things and acts of wickedneſs) I ſay, the Light ſheweth, <hi>that he ſhould not be worſe than the beaſts of the field,</hi> in ſuch <hi>words</hi> and <hi>works,</hi> or <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes</hi> of <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> and <hi>Gluttony.</hi> Which Light in all <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> never conſented to any <hi>act of filthyneſs, beaſtlineſs,</hi> or <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> but in all doth ſtand near the Soul, telling the Soul the <hi>evil of ſuch things;</hi> ſo theſe two being joyned together, (to wit) the Light of the glorious Sun of the Soul, and the Soul it ſelf to the Light in true knowledge of any thing, I call <hi>Conſcience,</hi> becauſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> properly and rightly importeth <hi>a joynt knowledge, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> and <hi>witneſs,</hi> by two knowing properties in <hi>Mankind</hi> of the <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil</hi> of <hi>all words</hi> and <hi>works</hi> whatſoever are <hi>ſpoken, done,</hi> or <hi>wrought</hi> by them: Seeing then every man hath this Principle of knowledge <hi>in himſelf,</hi> given by the eternal Sun of the Soul, as a meaſure of Light <hi>into their immortal Souls,</hi> hereby they come to know the nature thereof, according to the meaſure thereof; and in it diſcerning the vaſt multitudes of Mankind (which are not united to the Light) to be <hi>in the beaſtlineſs</hi> and <hi>evils</hi> which the Light of the Sun of the Soul doth <hi>reprove, judge,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn;</hi> hereby they may know <hi>in themſelves,</hi> that the nature of man is contrary to it, being <hi>very ſinful</hi> and <hi>abominable</hi> in <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>beaſtlineſs:</hi> So touching the contrariety, as to the place where it is found, briefly this is the ſum in anſwer; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>It's found in the inward parts, known in the Conſcience, and diſcovered by the Light, which ſheweth all things in the day of what co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and nature they are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order therefore to the true and pure Knowledge of the eternal Sun of the ſoul, it is abſolutely neceſſary for all people to underſtand, That nothing <hi>corruptible</hi> can ſee that <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Brightneſs</hi> which <hi>is incorruptible,</hi> to diſcern aright what it is, that they may not be alwayes ſeeking, and never come to find,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98353:4"/>
               <hi>and ever learning, but never able to come to the true Knowledge;</hi> ſeeking in the backward way, and learning in a Book of Lyes. And next to know, that man's ſtation is <hi>in ſin</hi> and <hi>corruption,</hi> in abſolute contrariety to the <hi>Pure Nature</hi> of <hi>Incorruption,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently hath <hi>no unity</hi> with the Glory of the <hi>Incorruptible One,</hi> nor hath the true knowledge of Him, and therefore in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, he worſhippeth <hi>he knows not what;</hi> which if, contrariwiſe, all were <hi>united</hi> in the Life, to the Life and Glory of the <hi>Eternal Sun</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> then would they all know that <hi>Incorruptible One,</hi> and accordingly worſhip in the <hi>true Knowledge</hi> of Him, who is the <hi>Eternal Brightneſs, Glory</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> over all things.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that no man knowes aright, but he which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed <hi>out of Corruption,</hi> and conſequently not worſhippeth aright, <hi>being in Corruption,</hi> the next thing that is needful to be informed of, is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>How, and by what means all men may come to be redeemed out of the ſtate</hi> of Corruption, <hi>thereby to have a true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of, and unity in Life with the</hi> Incorruptible One, <hi>and ſo to worſhip aright?</hi> By which aſſuredly all Nations will come to be of <hi>One heart, mind</hi> and <hi>ſoul,</hi> ſeeing the cauſe of <hi>Variations</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> may hereby be perceived to ſtand in the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Corruption, Sin</hi> and <hi>Tranſgreſſion;</hi> which if all come to be <hi>redeemed</hi> out of, and <hi>united</hi> to the <hi>Life, Power</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Incorruptible One,</hi> muſt infallibly be united to each other, being all <hi>in Him,</hi> who is <hi>but one <hi>in Love, Peace, pure Life</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which purpoſe and glorious matter (tending to the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Bleſſing of all Nations and Peoples upon the face of the Earth) I (as followeth) hold forth and ſhew that plain and eaſie path (of which it was propheſied to the <hi>Jews</hi> that it ſhould be revealed) <hi>in which the wayfaring men, though fools, cannot erre;</hi> which leadeth <hi>out of Tranſgreſſion</hi> into a pure life <hi>of Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</hi> Of which <hi>perfect happy way</hi> I ſpeak to every Conſcience of man, to whom this ſhall come, that it may witneſs <hi>in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> to this <hi>living</hi> and <hi>pure Path</hi> of the glorious Sun of the Soul and Eternal Power of Creation, whereby all ſhall be for ever left without Excuſe in the ſight of the Eternal Sun, who hate and refuſe the way, and by the Power of the Eternal Sun ſhall be judged, condemned and caſt out for ever from the Eternal Life and Glory thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98353:4"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Introd. </seg>
               </label> Man into whom a rational <hi>Soul</hi> is infuſed by the <hi>Eternal Power</hi> who created him (which is more <hi>than the Beaſts,</hi> or <hi>any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have</hi>) yet is <hi>brutiſh</hi> in his underſtanding and knowledge, occaſioned through the <hi>Law,</hi> or rather <hi>lawleſſneſs</hi> of <hi>his Luſts,</hi> which (as I have hinted) are worſe than <hi>beaſt-like,</hi> daily put in practice, both by utterance of words, and operation of acts, in his Life and Converſation; ſo that although his Creator hath provided him a <hi>Law,</hi> a <hi>Way</hi> and a <hi>Leader,</hi> by and in which he may come to be redeemed out of that ſad and miſerable ſtate and condition of his <hi>blindneſs, darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>ignorance</hi> of ſoul and mind, in which he is bound and chained by the power of Evil and Corruption (which I call the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> inaſmuch as that ſpirit is the original and principal cauſe) yet he giving more way <hi>unto the Power of Darkneſs,</hi> than yeelding <hi>unto the other Power which is Light,</hi> hath loſt the <hi>true Way,</hi> and erred from the <hi>true Guide and Conducter</hi> (which is able to lead him into an <hi>unity</hi> with his glorious Creator, who is the Power of Brightneſs) and entered into the <hi>Adulteration,</hi> and now lies wallowing like the Swine in the <hi>mire</hi> of <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>loathſomneſs</hi> of his own <hi>excrement,</hi> yea, rouling himſelf <hi>in the blood</hi> and <hi>pollution</hi> of his unwaſhed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, tumbling upon the ground of <hi>noiſomneſs</hi> and <hi>abominable ſtink,</hi> as a helpleſs wretch, without a <hi>ſhelter</hi> and without a <hi>ſhade,</hi> naked and miſerable without <hi>a garment</hi> or <hi>skirt of covering,</hi> without the <hi>Bread of Hope,</hi> or <hi>Water of Faith;</hi> beaten of his <hi>Foe,</hi> without <hi>hope of Redemption from his Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>bruiſed of his Enemy,</hi> without <hi>belief of his Reſtoration unto his firſt innocent Freedom;</hi> and thus ſtands bound unto <hi>death</hi> in the <hi>heavy chaine of captivity:</hi> and alas, poor miſerable blind man! though this is his loſt condition, yet he knows not, nay, nor perceives it not, and ſo layes not his miſery to heart, which is his double fetters of Iron; ſo though he hath a <hi>feigned hope</hi> and <hi>imagined faith</hi> in himſelf, yet being in <hi>the Adulteration</hi> from the Life of his <hi>Creator;</hi> as his life <hi>is ſinful,</hi> ſo his <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> in that corrupt nature is <hi>utterly deceivable,</hi> which can never unite his ſoul again to his Creator, but fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently periſh it everlaſtingly in the darkneſs under which he is held <hi>through ſin</hi> and <hi>corruption.</hi> And though thus hath been the ſtate of man almoſt from the Creation in the beginning, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs it hath pleaſed the Eternal Wiſdom <hi>now <hi>in theſe latter
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98353:5"/>
dayes</hi>
               </hi> (as it was propheſied of to the <hi>Jews) to open a path, wherein man may return again unto Himſelf in that pure and perfect ſhape and likeneſs in which he was created by his Glorious Power:</hi> In order to which <hi>Return</hi> through the <hi>living Way,</hi> and leading by the <hi>true Leader,</hi> I hold it in eſtimation of the Eternal Wiſdom and Counſel, firſt, to ſhew all the <hi>Indians, That Man in the beginning was created <hi>holy</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>not in ſin</hi> and <hi>corruption;</hi> which in this manner they may all plainly underſtand, <hi>viz.</hi> That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Eternal Power and glorious Sun of the Soul is in Himſelf <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>incorruptible</hi> in Life and Nature, could not therefore create a thing <hi>corrupted</hi> ſimply ſo, (that is to ſay) <hi>made in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in his hand, without becoming corrupt himſelf thereby;</hi> which is impoſſible that ever that ſhould be, Becauſe, as his <hi>Eſſence</hi> is <hi>Eternal <hi>from all Eternity,</hi>
               </hi> ſo his <hi>Nature</hi> is <hi>immutably</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably pure.</hi> And again, Becauſe He being the <hi>Eternal Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> who made <hi>the Sun</hi> in the Firmament of the Heavens <hi>a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious brightneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> glorious <hi>Lights</hi> in their places, which are viſible Creatures to the corruptible eye of Man, it would not ſtand with his Wiſdom, as unto the retaining of his Glory in Himſelf, to beget <hi>an inviſible ſoul</hi> in an <hi>unclean, filthy</hi> and <hi>polluted ſtate,</hi> which was the <hi>greateſt</hi> of <hi>all Glories</hi> which were ever created: Wherefore, I ſay, for theſe three Cauſes, <hi>of his Purity, Immutability,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> ye may perceive that Man was created a <hi>pure Soul</hi> in the beginning, by <hi>His <hi>pure Power,</hi> in His <hi>pure Glory,</hi> through His <hi>pure Wiſdom,</hi>
               </hi> of which the <hi>Jews</hi> have the Record, written from the beginning in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Tongue, ſhewing at large Man's Creation in <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency,</hi> the Law that was given him in that ſtate, and likewiſe how he erred from the Law, and thereby became a ſubject of the Power of Darkneſs, droven from the Eternal Glory into the <hi>Curſe,</hi> whereby the whole Creation became a Curſe unto him, which at firſt alſo were bleſſed (of the <hi>Pure Eternal Brightneſs</hi>) unto Him; for, ſaith the Record, <hi>When He had made all things</hi> (ſpeaking of the Eternal Power) <hi>He ſaw that they were good, and bleſſed them:</hi> whence you may all underſtand, as Man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the ſtate of <hi>Corruption,</hi> all the Creation (which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>his Good, Bleſſing</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi>) are aſſuredly unto him as <hi>his Curſe,</hi> his <hi>Evil,</hi> and <hi>Bond of his Wo and Miſery:</hi> In know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98353:5"/>
of which, you may all come <hi>to ſavour</hi> and <hi>reliſh</hi> the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of my Salvation of you all, now <hi>forwarding you</hi> (in all willingneſs of the Spirit of Truth) <hi>to the Way,</hi> and the <hi>Conducter</hi> (which is able to guide and lead you all in the ſame <hi>true Way, out of Sin,</hi> and <hi>ſave</hi> and <hi>redeem you</hi> from <hi>Corruption,</hi> which was the cauſe of the Curſe) into the <hi>Holineſs, Purity</hi> and <hi>Incorruption,</hi> that all your <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers, People, <hi>Cattle</hi>
               </hi> and all <hi>created things, may become every-where bleſſed,</hi> they <hi>unto you,</hi> and you <hi>unto them,</hi> that the Glory may be with, and in all, as it was in the beginning, even henceforth, and for ever, and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> In which <hi>Illuſtration of the way of Redemption from <hi>Sin</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Curſe</hi> that it brought, I diſcover the firſt ſtep of Order, and Principle to the True Worſhip (which is) <hi>to bow down;</hi> To bow down <hi>in Heart, Mind</hi> and <hi>Soul <hi>to that Light of the glorious eternal Sun,</hi> which is given into your Souls <hi>for a Law, a Guide,</hi>
               </hi> and a <hi>Leader.</hi> Turn all your minds <hi>unto the Light in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> which diſcovereth in all your ſecret thoughts the things that <hi>are evil, ſinful</hi> and <hi>beaſtly,</hi> and not of the nature of the Holy and Glorious One; and when-ever you find in your ſecret thoughts the power of Corruption and Darkneſs, tempting to draw you <hi>reſignedly</hi> and <hi>reſolvedly</hi> into <hi>verbal</hi> or <hi>actual Sin</hi> and <hi>Tranſgreſſion,</hi> which is contrary to the Law and way of the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>incorruptible meaſure</hi> of the Light of your <hi>Immortal Souls; <hi>Take ye that Light for the guide of your minds,</hi>
               </hi> and in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you will come to feel a War of the two Powers in you; that as the Power of <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> (which is of the <hi>fleſh fleſhly</hi>) doth tempt you, ſhewing you the <hi>Delights, Profits</hi> and <hi>Pleaſures</hi> of that Evil unto which it tempteth you; the Power of the Light (which is of the <hi>Spirit ſpiritually</hi>) will ſtand up againſt it, repreſenting unto you <hi>the Evil of the thing,</hi> the <hi>Curſedneſs of the thing,</hi> and the end of the Evil, which cauſeth a <hi>Separation</hi> from the <hi>true Life of Glory</hi> and <hi>Salvation;</hi> So here, ſtanding in the Power of the <hi>true Guide,</hi> it winneth the Soul, and begetteth it into a greater Love and Affection with the <hi>Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Life</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> than with the <hi>Abomination</hi> and <hi>Evil,</hi> which cauſeth <hi>Everlaſting Darkneſs, Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Seperation</hi> from the <hi>Glory</hi> which endureth to all Eternity: Thus Man en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98353:6"/>
himſelf, drawing his mind more and more from out of all that which curſed is, <hi>into the Light and Power of Salvation <hi>within him,</hi>
               </hi> comes to be delivered <hi>from all Evil:</hi> For to this every mans Conſcience ſhall <hi>affirmatively</hi> anſwer me, That in the Light of the Soul (that cometh from the Glorious Eternal Sun) never was any Sin or Evil committed; but <hi>out of it,</hi> and <hi>contrary to it,</hi> every <hi>act</hi> of <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> hath been done and wrought by all men; wherefore, if all men take that for the <hi>true Way</hi> (which is not of the nature of Darkneſs) and the ſame for the <hi>true Guide</hi> and <hi>Conducter</hi> (which is not of the nature of Sin, but in its nature contrary to all Sin) giving up their Souls alwayes to be led in it, and guided by it; this muſt needs lead all from and <hi>out of all things</hi> which are <hi>ſinful</hi> and <hi>corruptible,</hi> into its proper <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> by its vertuous Power operating in the <hi>inward parts;</hi> for except it could ſave and deliver from all Sin, then it could not appear to be a Vertue of the Eternal Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, or elſe, that the Power of Darkneſs hath gotten ſuch a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, that it's become greater than the Power of Light, that created all things; which can never be that it ſhould ſo come to paſſe, becauſe the Power of Light <hi>is Eternal,</hi> even <hi>from Eternity</hi> to <hi>Eternity;</hi> but the Power of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> came in <hi>in time,</hi> and therefore of neceſſity muſt alſo have <hi>an end in time,</hi> and ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be infinitly the leſſer power: and ſeeing <hi>its end</hi> muſt come, I hereby direct <hi>all Souls</hi> unto the <hi>Way</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> by which it is to be brought <hi>to an end,</hi> to know the End thereof <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves,</hi> even <hi>in every mans particular Soul:</hi> And the Power <hi>that is to end it,</hi> muſt be a Power that is in nature <hi>oppoſit unto it,</hi> elſe it muſt alwayes be ſtrengthened, and never come to be ended: Now the Power that is oppoſit <hi>in Nature, Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Operation</hi> unto <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> is <hi>the Light,</hi> which (as aforeſaid) convinceth <hi>in the inward parts</hi> of <hi>all Evil;</hi> yet a little to illuſtrate its deliverance of the Soul from all Evil, in this lowly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered manner I ſhew, That the Light in the Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth of the crime <hi>of curſing words;</hi> the which being <hi>loved, owned,</hi> and <hi>delighted in the Convincement,</hi> delivers from the <hi>Evil</hi> that it <hi>convinceth of,</hi> through begetting a ſhamefulneſs and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in the Soul againſt <hi>the Crime,</hi> and a <hi>pure love</hi> unto the <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>Thing</hi> that is found in <hi>nature, quality,</hi> and <hi>property,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98353:6"/>
               <hi>to the Crime</hi> from which the Soul is delivered; and here in the ſence of this Deliverance, in meaſure, from Sin, ariſeth a little hope of Redemption, which placeth a grain, or ſeed, of Truſt and Confidence in the ground of this Deliverance from one Sin, which though the Faith in that ſtate be but like a grain of Muſtard Seed, yet mark the end of that Faith, for in a <hi>pure Belief,</hi> through the experience that the Soul hath found in the Light, ſtrengtheneth it ſelf in an holy Love and Enclination to follow the <hi>pure Motions of it in all things,</hi> in which Faith (work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Love) it comes to find the perfect Effect; that as the Light was obeyed <hi>in the leaſt appearance,</hi> which accordingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from <hi>the leaſt Sin,</hi> the ſame being obeyed, loved and followed <hi>in every appearance</hi> (whereas it is <hi>pure, perfect, powerful,</hi> and of the nature of the <hi>Immutable Creature</hi>) cannot alter from its <hi>Nature, Property</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>ſaving</hi> and <hi>delivering <hi>from all Sin;</hi>
               </hi> So then this is the End of that grain of Faith, which is ſown in the Light, it <hi>removes</hi> from the Oppreſſed Soul <hi>the Rocks</hi> and <hi>Mountains</hi> of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Corruption,</hi> under which it is preſſed down, and <hi>breaks the Chains of Tranſgreſſion</hi> wherein it is bound in captivity, and <hi>ſets free</hi> in the liberty <hi>from Sin,</hi> and unites the Soul to the <hi>Original Glory</hi> from whence it is deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Wherefore this appears to be the true and undeceivable Hope in which the Soul witneſſeth its Purification, and the true Faith which gives Victory over Sin, which is the <hi>Bleſſed State;</hi> but all other Faith and Hope in the Life of Corruption, under the Power of Darkneſs, is that which deceivably periſheth the Soul, and is the <hi>Curſed State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, beſides this Declaration of the Power (which unto every Rational Intellect may appear <hi>plain, clear,</hi> and <hi>manifeſt</hi>) doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, thouſands (who of a truth this day do live in the Light, and are directly led and guided by it) together with this Witneſs, can experimentally teſtifie at large, that they <hi>in ſubſtance, Truth</hi> and <hi>very deed,</hi> have <hi>found,</hi> and conſtantly <hi>do find</hi> it <hi>redeeming, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering,</hi> and <hi>ſaving them</hi> from all <hi>verbal</hi> and <hi>actual Sin,</hi> and from <hi>all reſignations of mind unto Sin,</hi> in which formerly they were held under a <hi>woful Captivity</hi> by the predominating Power of Darkneſſe; theſe therefore are they to whom the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>living Sun</hi> of the Soul is <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>rightly known;</hi> who anſwerably <hi>to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98353:7"/>
the true</hi> and <hi>living knowledge</hi> do worſhip in the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>living Way:</hi> and theſe are all of <hi>one mind</hi> and <hi>ſoul,</hi> living <hi>joyntly</hi> and <hi>unanimouſly</hi> in one <hi>individual Spirit of Brightneſs,</hi> which created all Souls, and in this Life are at peace together for ever; So here are no <hi>Quarrellings</hi> nor <hi>Wranglings, Stirs, Brauls, Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſuing</hi> nor <hi>perſecuting one another</hi> for the viſible created things, which in the Worlds nature are corruptible and curſed; neither can ſuch a thing be among them, becauſe the free Law that is in them, leads to the <hi>nouriſhing</hi> and <hi>cheriſhing</hi> each other, as <hi>fleſh</hi> of the <hi>ſame fleſh,</hi> and <hi>bone</hi> of the <hi>ſame bone,</hi> being all <hi>Members</hi> but of one <hi>incorruptible body;</hi> And ye know, <hi>that no man hateth his own fleſh, but nouriſheth and cheriſheth it:</hi> much more (therefore) they, though many, yet being moulded from the <hi>corruptible</hi> into the <hi>incorruptible Spirit</hi> of Light and Glory, are become <hi>but one,</hi> living in the <hi>Unity,</hi> which is everlaſting, as Members meetly compoſed to ſhew forth the Glory of the Eternal Sun of the Soul, in the endleſs Life of <hi>Love, Concord,</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having ſhewed the <hi>Way</hi> or <hi>Redemption <hi>from Sin,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>ſanctifying</hi> the Soul unto its Creator, which leads unto the <hi>true Knowledge</hi> in a <hi>pure Union</hi> with its Creator: I would next ſhew <hi>the true and living Worſhip,</hi> according to <hi>the true Knowledge which I have received from him in the true Way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſtep of which, (as I have before ſaid) is, <hi>To bow down, and encline the Mind unto the Light, which inwardly enlighteneth the Soul;</hi> and the next ſtep after <hi>bowing down the Mind unto it,</hi> is, <hi>To wait in it, to know the Mind made ſubject in all Obedience unto it,</hi> whereby the perfect work of <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> may be thorowly wrought <hi>in you,</hi> that ye may be all made <hi>meet Veſſels, Tabernacles</hi> and <hi>Temples,</hi> to receive the <hi>Virtue into,</hi> which make the <hi>Sacrifice, Service</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> accepted of the Holy Eternal Power, before whom you draw near to offer; for except the <hi>Sacrificers</hi> and <hi>Worſhipers</hi> be of the <hi>nature</hi> of the Holy Power <hi>to whom they ſacrifice,</hi> that their Worſhips may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the ſame, both the <hi>Adorations,</hi> and the <hi>Adorers,</hi> are but a <hi>ſtink</hi> in the <hi>pure ſence</hi> of the <hi>holy Life</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Power</hi> and <hi>Sun of the Soul;</hi> and this you may all eaſily know: for if you put Chriſtal Water into a ſtinking noyſom unprepared Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98353:7"/>
the Water immediately corrupteth, and partaketh of the ſtink of the Veſſel, and being poured forth, is unfit then to be put into another clean Veſſel, leſt that Water (that was firſt ſweet in its own ſimple nature) ſhould defile the other Veſſel thereby; and the like is, if Excremental Water ſhould be firſt put into a clean Veſſel, &amp;c. And ſince it is ſo, much leſſe then can <hi>Corrupt Sacrifices</hi> or <hi>Sacrificers,</hi> have any Acceptance with the Holy One; for in ſuch a thing he ſhould be no more <hi>Holy,</hi> but as one that is joyned in <hi>unity</hi> with the Defiled and Unclean; which thing can never be, becauſe (as I have ſhewed) of <hi>his Eternity</hi> and <hi>Immutability:</hi> But ye, by waiting <hi>in the Light,</hi> in all <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>living Obedience,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l come (as pre-cited) unto the <hi>true purification</hi> and <hi>Renovation</hi> of the <hi>whole Mind</hi> and <hi>Soul,</hi> which bears the fleſhly Tabernacle, or Temple, about it.</p>
            <p>Again, Waiting <hi>in the Light,</hi> with your Minds <hi>turned in all ſinglneſs <hi>into it</hi> in your inward parts,</hi> being patient in that ſtate and condition of Waiting, and ſtanding a while in holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in that ſtep of the true Worſhip of the Eternal Power, (who ſpake to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſaying, <hi>To obey is better than Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi>) you will at length, in His Glorious good Pleaſure, <hi>come to feel</hi> the Riſing of His Glorious Power <hi>in you;</hi> which Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance I call, <hi>The Dawning of the Everlaſting Day;</hi> for it is to be underſtood, that all the time of the Darkneſſe, is the time of the Night, of which Sin and Corruption are the Clouds which bar and bolt men from the Glory of the ſhining Day; yet in that ſtate of the night there is a ſecret power ſet to rule, which diſpenſation is called <hi>the Light of the Moon,</hi> that as <hi>the viſible Moon</hi> was created <hi>to rule the Night</hi> in the viſible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; even ſo <hi>the Inviſible Light,</hi> was put into <hi>the Inviſible Soul, to rule in the time of darkneſs and ignorance,</hi> by which power (though the whole world ſtands in a <hi>Chaos</hi> of Confuſions, and becauſe of the <hi>darkneſs</hi> they know it not, yet) the World is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ſo as that every man thirſteth not after the blood of his neighbour, which if there were not an inviſible and <hi>ſecret Power</hi> of the <hi>Light</hi> ruling in the <hi>darkneſs of the Night,</hi> the whole Earth would outwardly become as <hi>an Ocean of Violation,</hi> and her face <hi>be overwhelmed with <hi>Blood,</hi>
               </hi> yea, what might I ſay? <hi>Murders</hi> would reduce <hi>all men</hi> to the <hi>laſt man;</hi> and what would he do? even
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98353:8"/>
               <hi>Murder himſelf</hi> alſo under <hi>despairation</hi> of the former works of his hands. But all men now coming to grow in mind and ſoul out of the Night, into the glorious Light of the Sun of the Soul, which opens the <hi>Everlaſting Day,</hi> through waiting in it will come to feel the riſing of the Power unto a greater beauty and ſplendor, whereby they will come to ſee the Light of the Moon to become as the Light of the Sun which is ariſen in the open day, and finding the operation of it encreaſing in the inward parts, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them forth either into brokenneſs and contriteneſs of heart, or the ſpiritual praiſe of the Eternal power, or forcing them to pour forth Supplications and Prayers unto Him, or in his dread to ſound the Trumpet of his Voice, declaring his <hi>Jubilee</hi> and acceptable year, which is at hand; this I ſtill call the <hi>riſing of the Eternal Sun in his glory and brightneſs in them,</hi> and they in this performing the duty required of them, the which they having fulfilled, quieting themſelves as it falls in a ſphear or degree lower; here unto them the Promiſe is fulfilled (which was propheſied of to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſaying) <hi>from the riſing of the Sun, to the going down of the ſame,</hi> Incence and Sacrifice ſhall be offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Temple of the Eternal Power.</p>
            <p>Moreover, As all men abide in the ſame Power of the Riſing of the <hi>External Sun,</hi> through a <hi>careful</hi> and <hi>conſtant watch</hi> of the mind in it, they will come to ſee it <hi>ariſe in ſuch a glory,</hi> that as firſt the <hi>Light of the Moon</hi> that ruled the night, became as the <hi>Light of the Sun</hi> which ruleth the day; So the Light of the day that is now ſpring from on high, ſhall be as the Light of ſeven dayes, abiding as an <hi>Everlaſting Glory of Brightneſs,</hi> even <hi>for ever and ever;</hi> and then will their Maker make his Tabernacle among them, and they ſhall be his Temple and Habitation, and he will be their <hi>Dwelling, Reſt, Peace, Joy, Life</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> eternally, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Hereby all men may ſee the true Worſhip ond Sacrifice, what it is, and in what Life and Power it is to be performed to find acceptance and anſwer; concerning which, if any ſhould ſay, that I have neither told them the <hi>matter,</hi> nor the <hi>manner,</hi> nay, nor the <hi>times</hi> plainly in which man ſhall worſhip in Prayers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw, </seg>
               </label> To ſuch I anſwer. Touching the <hi>matter of Prayer,</hi> It is to be underſtood, that Prayer <hi>is a <hi>Petition</hi> or <hi>Deſire</hi> poured forth for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98353:8"/>
ſomething that is needful, either to a mans own particular ſtate and condition,</hi> or elſe, <hi>that is neceſſary for other men.</hi> Now ſeeing the whole Creation ſtands in the alone diſpoſal of the glorious Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Cretor of all things, he therefore knows beſt what is needful unto every mans eſtate, which no man of himſelf doth know, neither can know what is neceſſary for himſelf, or any other Soul, but by the pure and immediate openings of the Light in the Soul, which purely doth proceed from the eternal glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wiſdom; therefore I teach no man <hi>words,</hi> but labour to lead all men to the <hi>underſtanding</hi> of the <hi>eternal Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Power <hi>within them,</hi>
               </hi> in this Light <hi>to wait,</hi> that in his Life they may feel the Riſings of the Power of his Wiſdom, which then may give utterance of words unto a man, that were never known before by a man, even ſuch words as ſhall be ſuitable to the ſtate of want either of himſelf or others, and ſometime alſo for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all ſouls in the <hi>bleſſed ſtate:</hi> all which (in the good time of the Eternal Wiſdom) ſhall be anſwered, who cannot deny himſelf, nor that which is of his own Nature, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in his own Life and Power: So then this in brief, no man <hi>of himſelf,</hi> knows what to Pray for <hi>as he ought,</hi> but the Spirit of <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Eternal-Wiſdom</hi> helpeth the ſanctified man's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities (that is to ſay) his weakneſs of knowledge, and giveth unto him either <hi>ſighs, groans, thoughts,</hi> or <hi>words,</hi> which anſwereth his Eternal Will in the Power of Wiſdom, which is the true matter of Prayer, whereby every man's Formality and Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhips comes to be aboliſhed; wherein alſo much may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as to the <hi>manner</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> ſeeing it leads out of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed words</hi> and <hi>times,</hi> that likwiſe ſtand in the adulterated will, wholly into the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>time</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom,</hi> in which ſtill, as a motion, is inwardly found the matter was given, and ſo his purpoſe comes to be revealed and known.</p>
            <p>In this order of Worſhip all People may be thorowly ſatisfied, That that which a man receives <hi>in the Eternal Power,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom,</hi> into a <hi>ſanctified Veſſel,</hi> is a <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> at a real certainty and aſſurance, and in no wayes <hi>dubious,</hi> and therefore may well be <hi>believingly received,</hi> and <hi>perfectly owned by a man,</hi> whilſt all other ſort of Worſhip (if the eyes of men were but a little open to ſee it) muſt needs <hi>be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98353:9"/>
doubted,</hi> becauſe it is of that which a man knows not what, nay nor can ſay that his <hi>method, matter, time,</hi> nay, nor yet his own <hi>perſon</hi> or <hi>ſoul</hi> hath any acceptance of the unknown thing that he doth worſhip in his vain imaginations.</p>
            <p>Yet it is in me to inſtance another uncovered Caſe, that in its nakedneſs every man may diſcern between <hi>the true</hi> and the <hi>falſe Worſhip,</hi> and accordingly chuſe <hi>the better,</hi> if their hearts can take an affection <hi>to the better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All People upon the face of the Earth may take one <hi>ſet form of words, manner</hi> and <hi>time,</hi> and in that cuſtom pray all dayes of their lies, and yet <hi>live</hi> and <hi>dye</hi> in <hi>enmity</hi> one to another, as it's this day manifeſt among many Sects that have <hi>ſet-forms of words, manner</hi> and <hi>times</hi> appointed for Worſhip, yet are of theſe minds; ſome of them flattering others of their Brethren and Fellow-worſhippers to their faces, whilſt they hate them in their hearts, and revile them behind their backs; And others of them there are, that love one another <hi>to day,</hi> for the ſake of the <hi>corruptible things,</hi> and the ſame perſons <hi>on the morrow</hi> ſeen fighting <hi>one</hi> againſt <hi>another,</hi> to gain the moſt of the <hi>corruptible things,</hi> or a ſeat of preſumption one above another, and ſo reſt in <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> one towards another, even unto death; this is the ſpirit of the power of darkneſs, and all the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Worſhips in it</hi> ſtand in the <hi>adulteration</hi> and <hi>ſeparation</hi> from the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Eternal, Immutable, Love,</hi> and therefore is abſolutely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to be <hi>the Curſed ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all People drawing to worſhip <hi>in the Spirit of the Power of Light,</hi> which is <hi>the Eternal vertue of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Vnity,</hi>
               </hi> here muſt certainly be found <hi>unanimous prayers</hi> with <hi>joynt hearts;</hi> or rather (as I have formerly ſhewed) with <hi>one heart</hi> and <hi>ſoul,</hi> becauſe the <hi>one Spirit</hi> and <hi>power of Love,</hi> makes all but <hi>of one ſoul;</hi> ſo to every <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Supplication</hi> in this Spirit, all ſouls in the ſame Spirit ſay, <hi>Amen</hi> in Truth; and when they are (according to every mans occaſion) ſeparated and departed in body one from another, yet ſtill <hi>they are together</hi> as <hi>one individual body</hi> in the <hi>individual Spirit</hi> of <hi>eternal love</hi> and <hi>unity;</hi> and thus they live in the body to the end, and thence for ever in the ſame Spirit reſt everlaſtingly out of the body without end: Theſe therefore I call the <hi>true Worſhippers in the true worſhip,</hi> and is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98353:9"/>
               <hi>Bleſſed State:</hi> Becauſe, as the firſt ſtands in the <hi>Adulteration</hi> and <hi>Degeneration</hi> from the true likeneſs of the holy Creator, and therefore impoſſible that that ſtate can have acceptance of him; ſo this latter mentioned, being in the true <hi>likeneſs,</hi> and therein finding the true <hi>Unity</hi> with the <hi>Power of Brightneſs</hi> in which the Worſhip is performed, and therefore muſt infallibly have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of him. From this Teſtimony (which ſtands not only in the <hi>Letter</hi> or <hi>Declaration,</hi> but in the power of an <hi>Endleſs Life</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi>) it appears without controverſie, that <hi>this,</hi> and only <hi>this latter of the Spirit of Love</hi> and <hi>Unity, <hi>is the Bleſſed State.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>A few things I have ſtill to ſhew unto the <hi>INDIANS,</hi> even ſuch of them who have not yet known the eternal glorious Wiſdom and Power of Creation, who of himſelf <hi>being without beginning of days, and end of time, <hi>made, compoſed,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>created all things <hi>in the beginning of time,</hi>
               </hi> that as they come to the true knowledge of him, may be turned from <hi>truſting in,</hi> or <hi>worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of</hi> any <hi>created Glory,</hi> and only <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>truſt in him,</hi> and come <hi>to worſhip him <hi>who is the Creator of every Soul on Earth,</hi>
               </hi> as likewiſe every viſible Glory that is placed in the Firmament of the Heavens. To all therefore <hi>that believe that the viſible Sun in the Firmament</hi> (which ruleth the viſible day) <hi>is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power by which all things are ruled and governed, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly do worſhip it, and the Moon that ruleth the external time of the night:</hi> I have to give you to underſtand, that in the whole Creation of Fiſhes and Worms, which are in the Waters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earth, together with the Worms that are in the Earth, the Plants, Trees and other living things that are upon the face thereof, with every Glory of the Heavens, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Sun Moon, Stars, Clouds of Rain, Hail</hi> and <hi>Snow, Dews, Winds, Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, Lightnings</hi> and <hi>Thunders,</hi> and whatſoever elſe may be ſenſed by the external <hi>Seeing, Hearing, Feeling, Taſting</hi> or <hi>Smelling</hi> of the body of man; I ſay, in all theſe the Eternul, moſt holy Wiſdom, and glorious Sun of the Soul is hid and vailed from man in his ſtate of Sin and Corruption, agreeable to what I have ſignified touching the contrariety between <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> and <hi>Incorruption, Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs, Purity</hi> and <hi>Beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe;</hi> the which I paſſe by for the preſent, drawing to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98353:10"/>
of a few things in the Light of the Day, wherein it may be underſtood, <hi>That the viſible Sun in the Firmament, is not the Supream Power,</hi> but that it is a <hi>Created Glory <hi>by the glorious Sun of the Soul,</hi>
               </hi> which is the <hi>Eternal, Inviſible,</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power.</hi> Firſt, from the nature of the <hi>viſible Sun,</hi> as it is a <hi>ſimple creature,</hi> which is <hi>hot, fiery, ſcorching,</hi> and <hi>burning;</hi> ſo that if there were not <hi>a Supream Power above it,</hi> ruling and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning it in a moſt glorious Power of Wiſdom, <hi>by ſending Rain in due ſeaſon,</hi> (which as a diſtinct and ſimple creature, is contrary to the nature of the Sun, being cold and moiſt) the whole Earth would become <hi>dried up,</hi> and utterly unfruitful, by which means every thing upon the face thereof muſt of neceſſity <hi>die</hi> and <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh:</hi> Wherefore in the Light of thee Sun of the Soul you will come to know, <hi>that the viſible Sun in the Firmament was made and created to ſerve man,</hi> and conſequently, <hi>not for man to how down and worſhip it:</hi> To ſerve Man thus, In one reſpect, as a light to the ſight of Mans fleſhly or bodily Eye, whereby he might tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, work and labour in the time of the day for the ſuſtenance of his outward being, as the Eternal Power in his Wiſdom hath appointed: And in another reſpect, tending alſo to Mans ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, the Eternal Wiſdom hath created it to ſerve Man, yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto the Earth of the ſtrength of its heat after the cold times and rain, drawing up from the Earth viſible and bodily ſhapes of Trees, Herbs, Corn, and all the good Encreaſe that the Earth in due ſeaſon doth yeeld.</p>
            <p>Again, It is to be underſtood, that the viſible Sun hath <hi>its Decree</hi> and <hi>Appointment</hi> from <hi>a Power <hi>above it,</hi>
               </hi> as it is manifeſt in its Riſing and Falling in ſundry Degrees, in <hi>Winter</hi> and <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and alſo by its conſtant courſe, in twenty four hours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the Earth, as a Circle; and ſo it is evident, that it is not its own Ruler and Governour, becauſe it is <hi>limitted to a courſe in all Seaſons of its Appointment,</hi> and therefore cannot be the Creator of any thing; but muſt of neceſſity be as the other Creatures, a Created thing; becauſe <hi>if one thing viſible be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>by a Power,</hi>
               </hi> certainly <hi>all things viſible muſt be created <hi>by the ſame Power,</hi>
               </hi> and conſequently <hi>the viſible Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon alſo;</hi> and that <hi>Man, Beaſts, Worms</hi> and <hi>Fowls</hi> were created by a Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power, is very plain, appearing by their ſeveral kinds
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98353:10"/>
and ſervices; and alſo being dead and rotten, their very duſt ſheweth of what they were made in the beginning; for whilſt their <hi>End</hi> is ſeen <hi>to be duſt,</hi> their <hi>Beginning</hi> or <hi>Creation</hi> muſt needs be underſtood to <hi>be of Duſt alſo:</hi> and the ſame Power that <hi>created <hi>the Earth,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>all that in it is,</hi> alſo <hi>created <hi>the Seas, and all that in them is,</hi>
               </hi> which is an Element contrary to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the viſible Sun, where the viſible Sun hath no power of burning, nor yet of making Food in the Deeps to grow at the bottoms thereof, to feed the Fiſhes that are therein: But the ſame Eternal Power and Wiſdom which filleth all places, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth a ſuſtenance as well for the Fiſhes in the Deeps, and all the Worms of his Workmanſhip, in their Bottoms, as He doth for <hi>Man, Beaſt, Fowls</hi> and <hi>Creeping-things</hi> that live upon the face of the Earth, unto which the viſible <hi>Sun, Moon</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> with the <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>Rain, Dews</hi> and <hi>Winds</hi> are ſervants, ordained and appointed by the Eternal and infinitly wiſe Creator of all things <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>inviſible.</hi> So then thus it may be clearly apprehended touching the Work of Creation, That none other can poſſibly <hi>be the Creator of all things,</hi> beſides a <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Eternal Eſſence</hi> which hath ſomething of a Being <hi>in all things</hi> in the <hi>Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Love,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of His own Life <hi>in Himſelf,</hi> by, and in which all things are upheld and preſerved in their due and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed courſes; for that which <hi>Created all things,</hi> muſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely be the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Preſervation of all things</hi> by his <hi>Continual Preſence;</hi> and undenyably alſo the death of all things, through the withdrawing of his Eſſence and Preſence; becauſe, as the <hi>Creator <hi>is but one,</hi>
               </hi> and his <hi>Life <hi>but one,</hi>
               </hi> doubtleſs therefore it is but his Life alone that doth or can <hi>give Life,</hi> his Preſence that <hi>gives Being,</hi> and <hi>preſerves Life;</hi> and the withdrawing thereof, the fall of all fleſh <hi>unto Death.</hi> Whereby it appeareth that his Glorious Wiſdom hath hid and concealed Himſelf from all the children and ſeed of Corruption, in the Decree of the Death of Man's Body by <hi>Sickneſs, Poyſoning, Drowning, Burning, Strangling, Wounding, Starving, &amp;c.</hi> for He having created all things, could make Man to live <hi>Under Waters,</hi> in <hi>Fires,</hi> not <hi>feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wounds,</hi> without <hi>Food, &amp;c.</hi> but his Glorious Power and Wiſdom will not be tempted, becauſe He will be reverenced and greatly feared in all things, and in Fear, worſhipped and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98353:11"/>
ſerved as the Creator of all things. Now, as for the <hi>viſible Sun,</hi> being naturally contrary to the Element of the <hi>Rivers</hi> and <hi>Seas,</hi> cannot poſſibly dwell with the Fiſhes that are in their Waters, ſo as to give them a conſtanr ſubſiſtance of Life, the which the meaneſt capacity may eaſily perceive, being a fiery Element; for, if a burning Coal of Fire be caſt into Water, it becomes quenched by the Water; or, if a Drop of Water be caſt into a great Flame of Fire, it conſumes to nought in a moment: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> that gives the Fiſhes their being in the Seas, nor yet Man his life upon the Earth, but the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> (as aforeſaid, together with the Fiſhes and all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) was made a ſervant unto Man, unto whom all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day are ſo continued, that he having the ſervice of all things viſible, yea, of the Glory of the Winds, which is an <hi>inviſible Creature,</hi> attending him with ſuſtentation, according to the Providence of the Glorious Eternal Wiſdom, ſhould with his whole ſoul ſeek and feel after his Creator, to attain unto the true knowledge of Him, therein to worſhip Him with <hi>all Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, Glory, Honour, Obedience</hi> and <hi>Praiſe,</hi> who as he made every thing to ſerve his Body (into which his Glorious Wiſdom infuſed a perfect and upright Soul, which was the greateſt of all Glories that in the beginning were created, in how much it had a true reſemblance in inviſible manner of the Inviſible Power and Glory that created it, of which none other creature had the like) could not expect leſſe from Man, than that he ſhould worſhip and ſerve his Eternal Goodneſs, with every Faculty of that Soul which He put into him. But yet I draw nearer to the moſt certain and true <hi>Witneſs</hi> in every Conſcience of Mankind, to remonſtrate (a little) the Glory of the moſt Glorious Sun of the Soul, ſhewing how it is a Glory in the moſt Glorious Part, where the external and viſible Sun reacheth not to enlighten nor ſhine about; That ſo, in a little meaſure, diſcerning the Excellency of <hi>the One,</hi> in Glory exceeding <hi>the Other,</hi> you may come to know aright the <hi>True, Living, Eternal, Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Supream Power, <hi>which ruleth and reigneth over all things.</hi>
               </hi> In proceed whereof, it is to be apprehended, <hi>That the Soul and Mind of Man <hi>is the moſt noble part of Man,</hi>
               </hi> in as much as every Member of the Body is acted as a continual Servant in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98353:11"/>
Obedience to <hi>the Motions of the Soul</hi> and <hi>Mind of Man;</hi> and alſo, becauſe the Soul is the <hi>Immortal Part,</hi> being not formed of <hi>a dead ſubſtance,</hi> as the Body was of the Earth, which returneth to Earth, but of an inſpiring Breath of Life, that for ever abides in a quick and feeling ſtate; the which Soul being taken out of the Body, leaves it (as aforeſaid) to a Converſion unto its firſt Mould.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeeing the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> only enlightens <hi>the Eye</hi> of fleſh, which is the <hi>ſervile part,</hi> and reacheth no further to ſhine about a Man, than <hi>without a Man,</hi> from which a Garment, Shelter, or Houſe, is able to ſhade, Cannot be the Supream Power and Glory; But the <hi>Eternal Sun of the Soul</hi> ſhines <hi>into the Soul,</hi> and <hi>enlightens</hi> the Inward Parts, and ſearcheth the Heart, and tryeth every ſecret Thought, and is ſecret unto all things, as having perfect knowledge of all things, from which nothing can be hid: For let a Man aſcend to the Skyes, it will reach him, and ſearch his dark heart there; or, if he go down into the Deeps, it will follow him and be with him there; and when the viſible Sun is ſet, and gone down under the <hi>Horizon,</hi> even at Midnight, the Light of the Soul can rip up every word and work (in the inward ſecret thoughts) of Sin and Evil, done and committed by a Man, and call the Soul to witneſs with it, which brings a Judgement and Condemnation in the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that ſmites a Man with <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Trembling</hi> within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> in the Firmament <hi>cannot do:</hi> for a Man may commit <hi>Beaſtlineſs</hi> and <hi>Murder</hi> whilſt the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> ſhines on him; which he cannot do in Countenance, nay, nor without Condemnation of the Light of the Sun of the Soul; and therefore the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> muſt needs appear to be infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhort of the Glory of the <hi>Inviſible Light</hi> that created all things.</p>
            <p>Again, If the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> had created the <hi>inviſible Soul of Man,</hi> then muſt it alſo ſearch and ſave it, and ſo be the greater Power, and of a Nature doing all things, which all may know that it is not ſo; for, in its proper nature, as a ſingle Creature, it doth but ſerve in the things (afore-mentioned) not blowing any Wind, nor raining any Water, nor can it ſo much as drive back one Cloud of all that the VVind bloweth over it, and ſo
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98353:12"/>
ſhaketh not the Trees, nor troubleth the Seas, which the ſtorms of Wind do; all which are created, ruled and governed by the Eternal Power and Sun of the Soul, of whom I ſpeak but as a Child and Suckling, He being in his Power, Wiſdom and Glory <hi>Infinite</hi> and <hi>Incomprehenſible;</hi> Yet in His Light I ſhew, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Soul of Man is ſo inferiour to Him, that the Souls of all Men in the Earth are comprehended of Him, as a drop of Water in the Sea, and as a Sand in the bottom thereof, (which every Man may feel <hi>within himſelf,</hi> in his own particular Soul) yet the low and poor Soul of Man reacheth to the heighth, yea, and far above the height of the prefixed Courſe and Circle of the <hi>viſible Sun's</hi> appointed daily Race; So then the <hi>viſible Sun</hi> (as I have ſaid) reaching not <hi>within a man</hi> to ſearch his Soul; nay, nor (as it's placed in the Firmament) neither by <hi>Ray</hi> nor light of <hi>Ray</hi> thereof can enter ſo much as into divers Artificial places, Caves or holes of Darkneſs made in the Earth, through the Invention of the Soul of Man, where the more <hi>ſervile part</hi> (to wit) the fleſhly body of Man can enter; being therefore in its glory ſo far (yea, and far more than I ſtand to mention) below the poor Soul that it is infuſed by a Power into the body of Man; Surely infinitly much more muſt it needs appear to be below the Glory of the Eternal Sun of the Soul and Power of the Creation, by which the Soul was firſt made in His own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Innocency,</hi> and comes again to be renewed into the ſame Image and Similitude, to live in the inviſible Glory of his moſt Glorious Life, in the perfect Inheritance, Fruition and Poſſeſſion of his unſpeakable Joyes and Pleaſures for ever and evermore.</p>
            <p>Now (to the Purpoſe of the Univerſal and Everlaſting Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) I am opened to ſpeak of <hi>Three Properties</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Brightneſs,</hi> That as all Men come to the <hi>Renovation</hi> into the firſt Similitude of <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Union</hi> with their Maker in that Glory, (as the way is plainly and eaſily held forth unto all, wherein they may ſo come to unite in their Maker as one ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Body for ever) may ſee, and ſit down in the Joy of their happy Benefit therein.</p>
            <p n="1">1. One Property of the Nature of the <hi>Holy One,</hi> is, <hi>Peace, perfect Peace,</hi> without ever having <hi>diſquiet</hi> in himſelf. All
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98353:12"/>
Souls therefore uniting to the principle of his Brightneſs <hi>in them,</hi> and dwelling in it as He abideth and reſteth in Himſelf, will come to ſee themſelves ſwallowed up (as in a bottomleſs and endleſs Ocean) in the ſame property of his Nature, <hi>(viz.) <hi>in Everlaſting Peace of the Soul, felt and enjoyed inwardly,</hi>
               </hi> which will wrap up all Souls in ſuch a height above diſquiet, or any thing of that Nature that is adulterated from the Holy Similitude, that all will chuſe that their Earthly Members may dye, (that their Souls may for ever poſſeſſe the Peace) rather than to live in the body of fleſh, to break the <hi>Peace</hi> of their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Souls, or the <hi>Peace</hi> of any of the Souls of the Spiritual Body of <hi>Peace,</hi> to whom (in the Eternal Peace) they are united, which is the immeaſurable ſtate of Bleſſing, paſſing all Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Property of the Nature of the <hi>Holy One</hi> is <hi>Love, perfect Love</hi> without <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> or <hi>Envy</hi> in Himſelf. All there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uniting unto the Power of <hi>Reſtoration</hi> unto the <hi>Glorious Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> will come to ſee the <hi>Eternal Love</hi> feeding, and ſaving his Enemies; and the Reſtored being of the ſame Similitude of their Maker, muſt in that reſpect do as their Creator doth, <hi>love</hi> and <hi>feed Enemies;</hi> for they cannot do otherwiſe, being of the Bowels of their Maker: And whilſt this Spirit <hi>loveth Enemies,</hi> much more muſt <hi>love the united in the Love unto it:</hi> if it cannot <hi>hate</hi> not <hi>envy Enemies,</hi> much leſs the <hi>united Friends:</hi> But all in this Spirit are full partakers of the <hi>unſpeakable Bowels</hi> of <hi>Eternal Love</hi> to each other, which is the immeaſurable ſtate of Bleſſing, paſſing all Underſtanding.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Another Property of the Nature of the <hi>Holy One,</hi> is <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, perfect Mercy</hi> without <hi>paſſion of Cruelty</hi> in Himſelf. All therefore joyning to the Power of the New Creation, will come to ſee the Power of <hi>Mercy,</hi> which is able to rent all Hearts perceiving it; for whilſt Man hath turned in Cruelty (even unto murder of the ſighing and groaning meaſure of the Light in himſelf) againſt his Creator, (who firſt gave the meaſure in the bounty of his Everlaſting Love, that Man by it ſhould be led to be like Him [the Giver of it] in holy merciful bowels) Yet, as in Mercy upon Mercy, hath now laſtly provided Him a Voice to call unto it, as a crying Bloodſhed upon the Earth,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98353:13"/>
and alſo to awaken his Bloody Soul that ſhed it, drawing his Soul near unto it, to reconcile himſelf with the Soul in and by it, though the Soul hath treacherouſly dealt with him and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therouſly fought in Rebellion againſt him. This ſhews <hi>Mercy <hi>to Enemies,</hi> Pitty <hi>to Rebels,</hi> Compaſsion <hi>to Bloody Traytors;</hi>
               </hi> wherefore, as all come to Unite unto the Power of Mercy, to be led into the true Image, and accordingly in <hi>Union</hi> with the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Fountain of Mercy, not one will be able in it to do a thing contrary to the nature of it. But the whole World comes to be as one intire glorious Body of <hi>Mercy, Pitty</hi> and <hi>Compaſſion,</hi> whereby no <hi>Diſtreſs, Languiſhing, Want</hi> or <hi>Miſery</hi> will be found upon the face of the Earth, which is the immeaſurable ſtate of Bleſſing, paſſing all Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Haply ſome may ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That it is evident, that <hi>Peace, Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> is the immeaſurable ſtate of Bleſſing, paſſing all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and therefore <hi>Diſcord, Envy</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> being the three quallities in contrariety, muſt be the woful eſtate of the Curſe; yet may deſire more largely to know, How the Curſe came, through an opening of the Original Cauſe and Univerſal Chain of</hi> Diſcord, Envy <hi>and</hi> Cruelty, <hi>which is the Curſed State?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Introd. </seg>
               </label> There is but <hi>One <hi>Original Good</hi>
               </hi> (as I have plainly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted) who created all things, and put into his creature, Man, that living part that ſenſibly thinketh, which is called <hi>the Soul</hi> and <hi>Mind,</hi> the which he created in an infinite degree below his immutable holy Eſſence (who can never change from his pure Nature to think in Himſelf a thought of Evil, yet he knoweth the thoughts of Evil in every Man's Heart) For though He made it in his likeneſs, <hi>pure, clean, holy, innocent</hi> and <hi>wiſe,</hi> yet made it in none other ſtate, than that he ought to know, that it had a <hi>Creator</hi> and <hi>Maker,</hi> and, by whoſe Power, that made it, could only be kept and preſerved in the ſimilitude of Him that created it; for being put into a body of fleſh, he gave it a ſenſe of Feeling there, as likewiſe in it a ſence of the reſt of the Creation, as <hi>Beaſts, Fiſhes, Fowls, &amp;c.</hi> to whom this was the ſubſtance of the <hi>firſt Comandment</hi> given him in his ſtate of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, <hi>That he ſhould not go in his Mind</hi>
               </hi> (out from the Power that created him a <hi>living Soul) <hi>into the fleſh for knowledge or pleaſure,</hi>
               </hi> for thereby he ſhould adulterate his Soul <hi>with the fleſh,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98353:13"/>
and ſo both the <hi>Soul</hi> and the <hi>fleſh</hi> become a <hi>Corruption</hi> and <hi>Curſe</hi> of <hi>Death;</hi> and in ſo doing he ſhould go from the Likeneſs of his Creator, who cannot go out of Himſelf into any creature for knowledge or pleaſure; But Man's Soul entring into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation with an aſpiring Concupiſcence in the feeling of his own fleſh, yeelded to know, and gave himſelf thereinto, and ſo became as a wedded ſpouſe unto Corruption; in that day was <hi>his firſt Evil,</hi> and the Birth of the <hi>firſt Devil;</hi> whereby it may be underſtood that the Eternal Wiſdom never derogated from his Glory of Holineſs in the Creation, ſo as that any man may ſay, he created a Devil immediately in his hand, which could never be (as I have formerly ſhewed more largely) by his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Holineſs, Immutablity and Wiſdom, but creating all things in themſelves mutable, even Man's innocent Soul alſo in it ſelf mutable as well as any other of the Creatures, and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Immutability onely in himſelf, that Man might know Him as his Maker, and ſo live only in Him, as the Immutable One, in his Holineſs, Wiſdom, Life, Glory and Joy; but he letting forth his Mind out of the Immutable Power of Wiſdom and Preſervation, became (as aforeſaid) <hi>an Evil-doer,</hi> and then <hi>his Thoughts</hi> were not like unto the <hi>Thoughts of his Maker,</hi> nor his <hi>Knowledge,</hi> nor <hi>Nature,</hi> like unto that in which <hi>he was created,</hi> but all his Faculties alienated, degenerated and ſeparated in the <hi>Adulteration,</hi> from the Likeneſs, Life and immutable Power and Wiſdom of his Creator; ſo that being the firſt <hi>actual Evil,</hi> muſt needs be the birth of the <hi>firſt Devil,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Devil</hi> is that Mind that doth evil in every man; and therefore nothing could be called <hi>an Evil-doer,</hi> until an Evil was firſt done and committed; which I ſpeak, to the end of ſtopping and putting an end to <hi>all blaſphemous ſuppoſitions</hi> and <hi>imaginations,</hi> and of ſanctifying the Name of the Holy One (in the eyes of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) whilſt I ſpeak of Him in the Glorious Power of His Wiſdom in the Work of his Creation. Thus then as followeth in Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Man's <hi>Adulteration</hi> from the vertue of the Life of his Maker, alienated the Faculties of his Soul, and brought upon it horrid Darkneſs and Confuſion, which ſpread over him, as an extream and mighty Power, until which there was no <hi>Enmity, Envy,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98353:14"/>
Diſcord</hi> nor <hi>Cruelty</hi> known in the Earth, but man was at <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity</hi> in his Innocency with the Holy One; Therefore the Original Cauſe of <hi>Diſcord, Envy</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> was <hi>Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and the Chain thereof to this day among Men is <hi>the Power of Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſake therefore of your <hi>Redemption,</hi> I am again preſſed in Spirit, to remind all with the Power that breaks the <hi>curſed Chain of Darkneſs,</hi> which is <hi>the Light,</hi> that is able to do it, (as all draw their minds into it, and dwell in it in their inward parts) and reſtore again into that ſtate which was before Tranſgreſſion was, in the perfect Freedom and Liberty from <hi>Envy, Enmity, Diſcord</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> in the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Brightneſs</hi> of <hi>Innocency,</hi> where the Wiſdom comes to be received which keeps and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the <hi>Peace, Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> in the Everlaſting Power and Vertue <hi>of Life:</hi> and here <hi>the Earth</hi> that once was the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> becomes the <hi>Footſtool,</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> becomes the <hi>inherited King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> for ever, which cloatheth the Soul with a Garment ten thouſand times ten thouſand fold brighter than is the Glory of the <hi>viſible Sun;</hi> for the Rayment is the perfect Glory of the Eternal Splendor, which wraps it up as with the ſwadling of the Rainbow of Joys, which is the Eternal Fruit and Benefit of the Bleſſedneſs of its Change, from the nature of <hi>Diſcord, Enmity</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> to the Spirit of <hi>Peace, Love, Vnity</hi> and <hi>Mercy;</hi> from <hi>Corruption</hi> to <hi>Incorruption;</hi> from <hi>Folly</hi> to <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> from <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> to <hi>Light;</hi> from <hi>Condemnation</hi> to <hi>Iuſtification;</hi> from <hi>Death</hi> to <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet furthermore, for the opening of the Counſel of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Salvation; O all ye <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> every-where throughout the Earth, know ye in your ſelves the <hi>Light</hi> of the Eternal Sun of Glory to be the <hi>bathing</hi> and <hi>waſhing Fountain</hi> that is able to make the Soul in every Thought even as <hi>white as Snow;</hi> and feel it <hi>in your ſelves</hi> as the <hi>Refiners Fire,</hi> which is able to purge you until you be made as pure as the Gold that is ſeven times tryed; and therefore wait in the Operation thereof, that you may ſee its bleſſed Effect, in which <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> will run down as <hi>Streams,</hi> and the <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of the Glory of the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> will cover the <hi>Earth,</hi> as <hi>Waters cover the Seas;</hi> and here you will come to ſee your ſelves
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98353:14"/>
as the Chriſtal Chanels through which the living Waters of the Fountain of Heaven will be a continual Current, the ſweet Streams thereof overflowing the bleſſed Vallies <hi>within you,</hi> and watering every Plant <hi>therein,</hi> making all things fruitful <hi>in you,</hi> and <hi>among you;</hi> fruitful in <hi>Truth,</hi> fruitful <hi>in Hope, Faith, Love, Mercy, Peace, Fear, Humility, Meekneſs, Patience, Content, Prayer, Praiſes, Thankſgiving, Knowledge, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>all Vertue;</hi> this will be a Beauty <hi>in your Faces,</hi> and a Diadem of Glory <hi>upon your Heads,</hi> in which the Wonderful Counſellor will take pleaſure to ſpeak unto you in His Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Oraculous Language, which ſhall be <hi>but one</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Earth, and will open an Incorruptible Eye <hi>in you,</hi> even to ſee the Glory of his Eternal Face, which will overcome you with Joyes, and raviſh you with Eternal Pleaſures, as a Generation that is carried up out of the Earthly Places: Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I cannot expreſs the Sweetneſs, as my Soul poſſeſſeth it, <hi>within</hi> in the Spirit, what beſides my own ſtate ſaved in the Eternal Sun of the Soul; Oh! my <hi>Raviſhed Mind,</hi> in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Day wherein Nations ſhall imbrace the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of all Love, and plentifully ſuck the Milk of her Breaſts, which gives the nouriſhment of Eternal Life. Oh! the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Conſolation</hi> which the Children of Brightneſs ſhall poſſeſs and inherit in the Boſom of the Eternal Glory, even for ever and evermore! <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, Are not the thoughts of this Glorious <hi>Salvation, Vnity, Peace, Love, Ioy</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure of Life</hi> (which may in this way be <hi>found, poſſeſſed</hi> and <hi>enjoyed</hi> to the End, among all People and Nations upon the face of the Earth; and in, and with the Glorious Brightneſs in the Heavens above) enough <hi>to perſwade, woo</hi> and <hi>compel</hi> all Souls (even with one draught of the Cord of Love) to <hi>receive</hi> and <hi>imbrace</hi> it? as they may ſink down into the Deeps, and conſider in what a good time their dayes are fallen into, wherein ſo glorious a Way is now come to be opened in ſuch <hi>plainneſs, clearneſs, nakedneſs</hi> and <hi>eaſineſs,</hi> wherein they may all attain to every tittle of the Benefits, yea, and a thouſand fold more than the tongue of man can mention, exceeding all that is before ſaid, inſerted and written? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly methinks, he that would miſs a Portion of the pre-cited Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98353:15"/>
and eternal joyous Inheritance for want of looking for it in the <hi>True Way,</hi> being ſo faithfully ſpoken unto him, as to <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him,</hi> and therefore ſo eaſie to be found, as not to look <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out himſelf</hi> to ſeek and find it, muſt not only confeſs himſelf <hi>to be a Fool</hi> in his own heart, but alſo <hi>as a Devil</hi> in his continual words and works, and ſeven-fold worthy of Condemnation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of Darkneſs and Death, unto its Pit of the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Wo</hi> and <hi>Torment</hi> for ever and ever. What therefore might I more ſay, <hi>that the <hi>Dead</hi> might <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>live?</hi>
               </hi> or that <hi>Rocks</hi> might <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>become hearts of fleſh</hi> to perceive and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand? for, the Word <hi>is quick,</hi> the Voice <hi>is piercing,</hi> and the Life <hi>is powerful,</hi> in and under which I reſt in the <hi>pure, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> and <hi>bleſſed Peace;</hi> hereby ſhewing forth, in meaſure, my Spirit and Soul (created anew in the Holy Love) unto <hi>all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> and <hi>Peoples,</hi> without reſpect of perſons, upon the face of the whole Earth; wherein I ſtand clear, whether they will <hi>hear</hi> or <hi>forbear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By that all <hi>Kings, Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> are (in the Light) come thus far; ſome may haply make forth their Convince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Truth, ſaying, <hi>It is certainly true and evident, that an Univerſal</hi> Peace <hi>and</hi> Unity, Love <hi>and</hi> Amity <hi>cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and purely had, held and enjoyed among all</hi> Nations <hi>beſides, in the</hi> one Principle <hi>that</hi> unites <hi>to the Eternal Power in his own Life and Nature; for He only being the Glorious Wiſdom that created all things, muſt neceſſarily be the</hi> alone Preſerver <hi>and</hi> Upholder <hi>of all things; and whatſoever ſtands united unto Him in the Life, abides in the Perfection of the</hi> Peace, Love, <hi>and</hi> Mercy <hi>of the Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Spirit of Wiſdom and Glory: And none other way can there be unto Bleſſing beſides the Light in the Conſcience, which is given of the Eternal Wiſdom for a</hi> Way <hi>and</hi> Leader <hi>unto all Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>But what doth this Light end and aboliſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It <hi>endeth</hi> all the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> with its <hi>effects</hi> and <hi>fruits,</hi> which ſtands in the <hi>Adulteration</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> from the Eternal and unlimited <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Brightneſs:</hi> It <hi>endeth</hi> all <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Traditions, Wayes</hi> and <hi>Worſhips,</hi> and whatſoever may be thought, that ſtand in the <hi>degenerate</hi> and <hi>curſed nature;</hi> and <hi>breaketh</hi> all <hi>Bryars</hi> and <hi>Bulwarks</hi> of <hi>limitation</hi> that ſtand in the <hi>Curſe,</hi> as a fence againſt its <hi>full, powerful</hi> and <hi>unlimited Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98353:15"/>
that through its free and unlimited Operation it may lead all unto the Bleſſed ſtate of <hi>Everlaſting <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with the Holy <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitted One,</hi> where there is no more <hi>Tranſgreſſion</hi> nor <hi>Curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if any particular <hi>King, Prince</hi> or <hi>Ruler,</hi> ſhould fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adde to his perſwaſion, ſaying; <hi>This is the Truth,</hi> and <hi>the true and living Way in which only the Holy One can be known and worſhipid aright; and therefore I am henceforth reſolved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in my whole Soul, to</hi> live, walk <hi>and</hi> worſhip <hi>in the ſame: But whereas I have a Kingdom, Province, or Territory under my Authority,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>What ſhall I do to theſe People to make them be all of this mind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Thou having found <hi>the true</hi> and <hi>living way,</hi> bleſſed art thou having found it, if thou walkeſt and abideſt in it; therein to be led from <hi>degree,</hi> to <hi>degree day</hi> by <hi>day, more</hi> and <hi>more</hi> into the likeneſs <hi>of Him,</hi> who anew createth thy Soul <hi>within thee;</hi> for herein thou ſhalt reap a plentiful harveſt of his Wiſdom in thy <hi>Inward parts,</hi> which will give thee in the Day of Brightneſs to ſee, that He draweth all <hi>into Himſelf</hi> with the Cords of the Power of Love in his Glorious Wiſdom, whoſe Counſel will accordingly inſtruct thee to retain the perfect ſimilitude of his Glory, and therefore ſhall <hi>draw all by the ſame love of Wiſdom,</hi> into the <hi>ſame Light</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and in none other Power ſhalt thou work with any man beſides <hi>that</hi> by which thy Maker worketh <hi>in thee;</hi> for elſe thou wilt degenerate and go utterly from the likeneſs of thy Creator, as the wicked and rebellious Rulers of the Earth do, to <hi>Envy, Impriſoning, Perſecuting, Killing, Murdering,</hi> and <hi>ſpilling of Blood;</hi> all which ſtand in the <hi>adulteration</hi> and <hi>ſeparation from,</hi> and <hi>in the <hi>curſed enmity</hi> to the Life of thy Creator,</hi> which is <hi>Peace, Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy;</hi> and thus, inſtead of ſeeking to draw others to Him, thou thy ſelf wilt run like a <hi>Fugative</hi> and <hi>Vagabond</hi> from Him, and bring <hi>guilt</hi> upon thy own head, by ſhortning the dayes of ſuch as thou doſt <hi>impriſon</hi> and <hi>perſecute,</hi> to whoſe Life thou art not able to adde a day; and for killing that which thou canſt not make alive again: And there alſo the <hi>weighty price of Souls</hi> will be charged grievouſly <hi>upon thee,</hi> for which thou canſt never make ſatisfaction; and if through <hi>thy Cruelty</hi> thou ſhouldſt <hi>turn any</hi> to thy ſelf, it is but unto <hi>that life</hi> which is <hi>wholly curſed;</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98353:16"/>
therefore keep thee towards <hi>all men,</hi> as thy Creator keeps to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>thee,</hi> loving <hi>all men,</hi> as He loveth <hi>enemies,</hi> and hath great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>loved thee;</hi> and wait upon thy Creator, praying to Him <hi>for all men,</hi> like as a long while He waited upon <hi>thee,</hi> for thus thou groweſt into His <hi>true Similitude;</hi> and (mark the end) in <hi>His Time,</hi> he who <hi>formed</hi> and <hi>renewed thy Soul in Himſelf,</hi> will do <hi>the like</hi> to many more of <hi>thy Region</hi> and <hi>Dominion;</hi> and then as the Soul of thy Maker was rejoyced in thy <hi>Return</hi> unto <hi>Himſelf;</hi> ſo wilt thou have an exceeding Joy in <hi>their Return unto Him alſo,</hi> for whom thy Soul <hi>travelleth</hi> and <hi>thirſteth</hi> in ſecret fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: And as in this <hi>Particular,</hi> ſo in <hi>every Particular Caſe,</hi> walk thee as one that is moulded into a <hi>new frame,</hi> like unto the <hi>Holy One</hi> thy <hi>Maker;</hi> and in ſo doing, thy Fruits will be abundant to His Praiſe, and He will take pleaſure to enrich thy Soul with His <hi>Everlaſting Vertue</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and his Spirit of Power and Glory will reſt upon thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet, in respect of the Univerſal Publick Service of the Holy One, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>How may it be ordered in relation to Aſſemblies and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Whereas the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> of all <hi>Power</hi> is but <hi>one infinit Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>of Love,</hi>
               </hi> all that draw into <hi>Unity with Him,</hi> muſt certainly draw into an <hi>infinit <hi>Love</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Vnity <hi>one with another;</hi>
               </hi> in which ſtate (that the Unity may be held in the Joy of Eternal Love) the Power of Wiſdom ſets in this Order, firſt, appointing <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Places for Publick Aſſemblies;</hi> and next, determining <hi>convenient Times,</hi> wherein the <hi>Congregations</hi> may be kept, not by <hi>conſtraint</hi> or <hi>violence;</hi> for as the <hi>Love</hi> of the Eternal Virtue and Power of <hi>Love</hi> is <hi>free</hi> in Himſelf towards every Soul; ſo requireth <hi>He</hi> that all Souls <hi>ſhould be like Him,</hi> ready <hi>in heart,</hi> and free <hi>in mind <hi>to aſſemble together,</hi>
               </hi> and not in any other <hi>way</hi> or <hi>manner;</hi> becauſe neither the <hi>Conſtrainer,</hi> nor the <hi>Conſtrained</hi> retains the perfect ſimilitude of <hi>his Love</hi> and <hi>Freedom,</hi> but are in the <hi>degenerated Will,</hi> wherein every <hi>Sacrifice is abominable.</hi> And when both <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> is appointed <hi>for Publick Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi> all that are <hi>united</hi> in the Eternal Vertue, as <hi>one Soul</hi> and <hi>Mind,</hi> and <hi>Members of one Spiritual Body,</hi> muſt needs <hi>congregate</hi> and flow together, to the end of <hi>nouriſhing</hi> and <hi>cheriſhing</hi> their own fleſh; for waiting together in the <hi>one Spirit of Holineſs</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98353:16"/>
               <hi>Eternal Power,</hi> the Power will ariſe <hi>in</hi> and <hi>among you,</hi> and the Word of Life will go forth of the mouths of many, on which the whole Body will feed, and by it be <hi>cheriſhed</hi> and <hi>nouriſhed</hi> unto a Life af <hi>Immortal Purity, Joy</hi> and <hi>Glory;</hi> So that when all have found the experience of this ſweetneſs in the Order of Aſſemblies, as we have found, will make <hi>them flow,</hi> even as <hi>we fly</hi> (in the Spirit of Unity) unto the <hi>Holy Congregations,</hi> diſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and appointed by the Spirit of Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Again, in reſpect of Government, <hi>Seeing the Creator of all things is an Infinit Wiſdom, muſt abſolutely therefore be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Order and not of Confuſion;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>By what Laws then ſhall all Nations be ruled and governed, for the preſerving all things in meet and pure Order?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> is of the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>Eternal Wiſdom;</hi> Therefore, in relation to the <hi>Love,</hi> which keeps in the <hi>true Order</hi> (whereby the <hi>true Government</hi> comes to be known) this may you all underſtand; He that created <hi>all Things</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> I call <hi>the</hi> KING <hi>of Kings</hi> and <hi>of Glory;</hi> is the <hi>One Almighty Ruler over all his Creation and Workmanſhip,</hi> and requireth that all ſhould be ſubject to his Government, whoſe Law is <hi>but one,</hi> which (as I have ſhewed) is written <hi>in the inward parts,</hi> which is <hi>the Light of the Sun of the Soul,</hi> that was before <hi>Tranſgreſſion was,</hi> and leads into that ſtate <hi>where Tranſgreſſion is not:</hi> This only is the <hi>true Law</hi> that is to rule <hi>in all inward parts,</hi> to rule <hi>all Minds</hi> which rules <hi>all Members;</hi> and the Minds being ruled <hi>by it,</hi> all the Members become ſubject <hi>unto it,</hi> whereby the whole World of Mankind comes to be drawn into the Likeneſs of the Life and Power that created them, in which ſtate <hi>Tranſgreſſion is not;</hi> ſo here the Law <hi>is a Saviour,</hi> and <hi>not a Judge:</hi> which Law thus teacheth, (to wit) <hi>Do unto all men, as ye would that men ſhould do unto you.</hi> And again, it alwayes teacheth, That all <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Iudges,</hi> ſhould keep <hi>to the true ſimilitude,</hi> like unto <hi>their Creator,</hi> in matter of <hi>Judgement,</hi> by a Law; and conſequently, not <hi>to judge any man</hi> in any other <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner,</hi> or by any other <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Law,</hi> than <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> that <hi>Law</hi> which <hi>judgeth</hi> and <hi>ſaveth themſelves</hi> in the Inward Parts, which ſtill draws <hi>to the Similitude,</hi> and preſerves the Soul <hi>in the likeneſs of the Eternal Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> that created it; So
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98353:17"/>
then, in caſe of <hi>Rebellious Subjects</hi> in a Land, that would live <hi>in a lawleſs life,</hi> of deſtruction of the <hi>King of Glorie's Creation,</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and preſumptuouſly, in <hi>Lewdneſs, Beaſtlineſs, Violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> or what other wickedneſs ſo ever; <hi>Kings, Pinces, Rulers</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> ſhall have no need <hi>to turn out their Minds from the Law <hi>within,</hi>
               </hi> to ſearch <hi>Books</hi> or <hi>Records</hi> (of their <hi>Lands</hi> or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) <hi>without them,</hi> to find a <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> ſuch Tranſgreſſors by; for that <hi>alienates</hi> and <hi>adulterates</hi> from the <hi>pure Similitude,</hi> ſeeing the Creator cannot go out of Himſelf <hi>into Books</hi> without Him <hi>for a Law,</hi> but keeping to the <hi>Inward Law</hi> of the Creator (that preſerves in the Glorious likeneſs) and judging all <hi>in it,</hi> and according <hi>to it,</hi> anſwereth the ſame <hi>in all,</hi> and leaves them <hi>without Excuſe</hi> in the ſight of the <hi>Eternal Searchers of all hearts;</hi> in which Judgment they hold <hi>the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with their <hi>Creator,</hi> and ſtand <hi>juſtified</hi> before Him, and by that of Him <hi>in all Conſciences,</hi> which anſwereth the Judgement of it: Seeing therefore it is evident, that the eternal Judge is <hi>but one,</hi> and his Law <hi>but one,</hi> the Judgement that is of Him in it, <hi>is the Bleſſed State;</hi> but that which is contrary to it, <hi>is the Curſed State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, it may be plainly underſtood, That he who made all Men <hi>in his own Eternal Wiſdom,</hi> certainly <hi>was,</hi> and <hi>is,</hi> the Wiſeſt to make a Law for all Men that he created, which in His Wiſdom (is evident) He accordingly <hi>did decree,</hi> and hath placed it <hi>in the Inwards,</hi> near unto the moſt noble part of Man, which ruleth all his Members, (to wit) the <hi>Soul,</hi> wherein all Tranſgreſſion <hi>comes firſt</hi> to be conceived, before any is ever brought to the birth. So then, he that altereth <hi>from his Law,</hi> and maketh <hi>another Law</hi> to judge Men <hi>by,</hi> contrary <hi>to that Law</hi> which his Creator hath placed near unto the moſt noble part of all Mankind, and even <hi>in his own Conſcience,</hi> as well as <hi>in the Conſcience of an another Creature;</hi> that very <hi>Ruler</hi> ſtands <hi>in the Preſumption</hi> adulterated and ſeparated from his Creator, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf as if he had a <hi>Wiſdom above his Creator,</hi> to make a <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> his creatures <hi>by,</hi> which is a moſt <hi>horrid Rebellion</hi> againſt his Creator, and his holy and juſt Law. <hi>Awake, awake</hi> therefore. O all ye <hi>Kings, Princes, Rulers</hi> and <hi>Judges</hi> upon the face of the whole Earth, and <hi>anſwer</hi> your Creator in this true point of Judgement.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98353:17"/>Now if the poor men ſhould make forth their Convincement of the Truth, ſaying, <hi>We are perſwaded of the Glory of the Truth of the Sun of the Soul, for we experience it in the inward parts, and can ſet our Seal to the</hi> Teſtimony thereof, <hi>to be altogether</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>and</hi> Pure <hi>within us; <hi>in which ſence of the</hi>
               </hi> Love <hi>of our</hi> Creator <hi>towards us, we are truly willing and deſirous to</hi> live <hi>and</hi> walk, <hi>ſo as that our Souls may be, made worthy of ſuch a glorious Infuſion and Inſpiration of the Eternal Love and Mercy: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>But what ſhall we do, ſeeing the Rulers of our Land ſtand in oppoſition,</hi>
               </hi>
               <hi>and we cannot ſo walk without an abſolute peril of ſevere Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſharp Tortures, loſs of earthly Eſtate, or Life it ſelf?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> He that <hi>created you,</hi> is the <hi>Eternal Power</hi> and <hi>Almighty King of Kings,</hi> who reigneth <hi>over all</hi> in the Kingdoms of Men; and giveth them to whomſoever he pleaſeth: Stand ye therefore in the Life of his Pleaſure, which is in that (whereunto you are inwardly directed) which begetteth and formeth you in the pure and perfect ſimilitude of your Creator; and there you will come to ſee Him <hi>to be the everlaſting Patience</hi> and <hi>Eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> which is a greater Felicity and Glory for you to know <hi>in your ſelves</hi> as being moulded into the ſame Reſemblance, and ſo united to Him in the Power and Life thereof, than the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of outward Liberty, poſſeſſion of Eaſe in the Fleſh, Earthly Treaſure, or Life it ſelf in the body; yea, a Heavenly Happineſs it is, infinitly ſurpaſſing all that ever can be thought of below the <hi>viſible Sun;</hi> the <hi>living ſence</hi> and <hi>feeling</hi> of which in the Eternal Power, makes the <hi>Impriſonment of the body <hi>a ſweet freedom of the Soul;</hi> the Tortures of the Body,</hi> the <hi>joyful plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Soul; <hi>the loſs of Earthly Goods,</hi> the purchaſe of an Heavenly Treaſure; <hi>and the Death of the Body of Fleſh,</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Glorious Life of the Soul;</hi> Thus for every <hi>finite Loſs,</hi> is reaped an <hi>infinite Treaſure of Gain.</hi> So then as ye grow into this Life, committing all things, <hi>Houſe, Goods, Silver, Gold, Wife</hi> and <hi>Children, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> into the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Everlaſting Patience and Eternal Content, you come to reign <hi>as Kings</hi> in the glorious <hi>Life</hi> of the <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> over all <hi>Earthly Kings,</hi> and they ſee it not, nor know it not; who perſecute you, being themſelves in the act of <hi>Perſecution adulterated</hi> and <hi>alienated</hi> from the Life of the <hi>Eternal Patience</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98353:18"/>
and <hi>Content,</hi> and in <hi>enmity</hi> to his power of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> which is the <hi>Curſed State</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> So you knowing your Advantage of Treaſure, and Prerogative of Dominion in the power of Patience and vertue of Content, ye may well ſay in your ſelves, <hi>As we live and abide in the fear of our Creator</hi> (which preſerves in the continual poſſeſſion of his Immortal Rewards and Treaſures of all Joys) <hi>we need not fear Earthly Kings nor Princes,</hi> nay, <hi>nor loſs of Lives, nor any other Creature: for here we perceive</hi> temporal loſſe, <hi>can be</hi> no loſſe <hi>unto us, but as an</hi> Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt-peny <hi>offered and given by us for the price of an <hi>Eternal Gain;</hi>
               </hi> And therefore <hi>we will run our Race in the fear of our Maker with joyfulneſs, holding the ſimilitude of his own Holyneſs; that if we are perſecuted, we will</hi> love <hi>and</hi> pray <hi>for our Enemies, even as our Creator</hi> loved us <hi>whilſt we were</hi> his Enemies; <hi>and we will</hi> bear with them, <hi>as he bore</hi> with us; <hi>and</hi> forgive them, <hi>as he hath</hi> forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us: <hi>Thus will we</hi> live, <hi>and thus will we</hi> dye: <hi>and the Name of our Maker be evermore ſanctified, hallowed, honoured and praiſed <hi>by</hi> and <hi>in us</hi> to the end, Amen.</hi> And ye being entered into this everlaſting bleſſed State, you ſtand (as I have ſaid) in his good pleaſure, <hi>who reigneth in in the Kingdoms of Men, and giveth them to whomſoever he pleaſeth;</hi> and then whoſoever turneth againſt you, to perſecute you, turneth againſt the pleaſure of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: And mark the battle, the <hi>Pot</hi> fighteth againſt the <hi>Potter,</hi> who will therefore <hi>break it to pieces</hi> in his ſore diſpleaſure: the <hi>Duſt</hi> fights againſt <hi>its Maker,</hi> who therefore will <hi>blow it away,</hi> even with the <hi>fierce Whirlwind</hi> of his <hi>utter displeaſure,</hi> and gain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a <hi>Renowned Glory</hi> over every rebellious Creature; for even now is He ariſen in his Jealouſie, and it is his Day <hi>to work,</hi> and none <hi>ſhall let;</hi> and he which rules againſt Him, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from the Throne; for He will ſet up an Everlaſting Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and Government, and of his own Scepter of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, even from end unto end of the four Winds of the Heavens. Seven-fold happy therefore is that Soul <hi>that beleives in Him,</hi> and <hi>ſuffereth for his Righteouſneſs ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not an unſpeakable ſhame, to a Ruler <hi>to perſecute <hi>innocent Souls, new created Souls</hi>
               </hi> in the Glory of the <hi>ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their Maker?</hi> Is it not a woful ſhame to Rulers, <hi>to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute them, that watch to <hi>recompence good for evil,</hi>
               </hi> and to ſhew
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98353:18"/>
the deeps of the bowels <hi>of Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> to ſuch as <hi>heaped up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them extream weights of Oppreſſion and Cruelty?</hi> Can Rulers anſwer the bonds of humanity in ſuch acts? Nay. How then can they anſwer the power of Sanctity in them?</p>
            <p>For the ſake of Edification of all Souls, to Three Queſtions more I am drawn forth (in the Light) to anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>What are the firſt powerful Operations of the Light in the Soul, after Convincement of Sin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>JUDGMENT, CONDEMNATION,</hi> and <hi>DEATH</hi> of the Mind of <hi>Tranſgreſſion;</hi> which muſt of neceſſity be, for the cauſe of the Righteouſneſs of the King of Glory, unto whom no life in Sin and Corruption can <hi>unite;</hi> for the Soul going into it, went out from Him into the <hi>Enmity</hi> againſt Him and His Law of Righteouſneſs, and no part of that can ever enter into Him, becauſe it was never of Him; and becauſe He hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed a righteous Law into the Inward parts, of neceſſity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there muſt be a power of Judgement to execute the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law (in the place that it is put) upon that which brake it, which Power in Righteouſneſs muſt abſolutely bring <hi>Condemnation</hi> upon that mind which is the <hi>Tranſgreſſor <hi>in man;</hi>
               </hi> and the <hi>Condemnation</hi> muſt as ſurely <hi>bring Death</hi> by the power of the <hi>Executor,</hi> that no part of that Mind may evermore live, but the Mind in which <hi>no Tranſgreſſion is,</hi> which was before <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion was,</hi> which muſt be perfectly wrought before Man can enter again <hi>into the firſt Similitude,</hi> to <hi>unite</hi> with the King of Glory. So here all may ſee the Judgement truly ſet up, and executed in the <hi>inward parts,</hi> bringing <hi>Death</hi> upon the <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor,</hi> produced the benefit of a moſt Bleſſed Fruit, <hi>(viz.) of Life, Peace</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> and openeth the door of the Fountain of <hi>Mercy,</hi> giving the perfect knowledge thereof, which then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth over <hi>Judgment;</hi> for which cauſe of <hi>Mercy</hi> the Eternal Wiſdom firſt inſtituted the Law and Power of <hi>Judgment</hi> to come, fulfilling Righteouſneſs in the <hi>Inward parts,</hi> which thus appears, bringing <hi>a Righteous Death</hi> upon an <hi>Unrighteous Life,</hi> that by its Death a <hi>Righteous</hi> may for ever <hi>live,</hi> wherein the Joy and Glory is partaked and inherited: So then in the <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Condemnation</hi> of <hi>that Life</hi> unto <hi>Death,</hi> the Power and Glory of <hi>Mercy</hi> appeareth in the wonderful Wiſdom, that it
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98353:19"/>
might be for ever <hi>loved</hi> and <hi>lived in,</hi> and the work of Wiſdom <hi>admired</hi> and <hi>prized,</hi> and the Worker of Salvation (in the Power and moſt Excellent Glory of <hi>Mercy,</hi> manifeſt in Judgement) magnified over all everlaſtingly without end, in all that love the Operation, and accordingly are partakers of the ſweet and happy Fruit of its Salvation, in which the Unity with the King of Glory is witneſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Of every frame of Soul, or faſhion of Mind in Man, which is the moſt <hi>certain</hi> of holding the <hi>Vnion</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with the King of Glory <hi>in Spirit?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Watchfulneſs <hi>in Fear</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Croſſe: <hi>Watch</hi>
               </hi> to fear the <hi>riſings</hi> of the <hi>Concupiſence</hi> which the Soul feeleth in the fleſh, towards the fleſh and the World, and alſo now laſtly towards the <hi>Devil,</hi> and there enter into that Internal Power, which ſtands in the Croſſe to the other Nature, which will daily ſlay <hi>every carnal Affection</hi> in the <hi>firſt ſuggeſtion</hi> and <hi>appearance,</hi> and break the <hi>Cockatrices Egg</hi> before the <hi>Serpent is hatched;</hi> and thus all will come to ſee that the <hi>inward</hi> and <hi>viſible Croſs,</hi> to the <hi>inward Mind</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> keeps the Soul clean out of the mind of the World and the Fleſh, in the mind of the Eternal Spirit.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Watch</hi> to fear <hi>in every Joy</hi> and <hi>Enjoyment</hi> of every <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Gift,</hi> leſt the Joy ſhould ſlip out of the <hi>true meaſure,</hi> and a ſence of the Glory of the Gift exalt the Heart above the meaſure of the Light, through which it <hi>comes,</hi> and in which <hi>the Unity with the King of Glory ſtands;</hi> and here all which come to ſee that Fear keeps every Joy and Enjoyment of Heavenly Gifts, perfect to the meaſure, wherein all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is witneſſed according to the proportion of all Gifts as they are given, and come down from the perfect Giver: So then the <hi>inviſible Croſs</hi> which keeps <hi>clean,</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> that keeps the Soul <hi>low</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> to the meaſure <hi>within in the Conſcience,</hi> will alwayes be found <hi>the ſafeſt frame</hi> and <hi>faſhion</hi> of every man's mind <hi>to hold</hi> the moſt <hi>certain <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with the King of Glory, as long as they are cloathed with the body of fleſh, untill it turns to the duſt from whence it came, and the Soul be from thenceforth cloathed and arrayed with the Glory of the Life of the King of Glory, even <hi>for ever</hi> and <hi>evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98353:19"/> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Whether Man</hi> (after being reſtored unto the Brightneſs of the firſt Similitude, and entred into Unity with the Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible Glory, through death of the degenerated part) <hi>may not fail from the Glory, and enter again into the Degeneration and Curſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> In the work of Creation it is to be known (as formerly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) that the Soul of Man <hi>ſimply</hi> was not created <hi>immutable,</hi> though <hi>clean, pure</hi> and <hi>holy,</hi> in a ſtate of <hi>Innocency,</hi> for the Eternal Wiſdom reſerved that <hi>Virtue, Power,</hi> and <hi>moſt glorious Property of <hi>Immutability</hi> in Himſelf <hi>only,</hi>
               </hi> that He above all things might be known as <hi>the Supream Power</hi> over all <hi>the creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed things,</hi> and accordingly <hi>feared, loved, obeyed,</hi> and <hi>lived in:</hi> which ſtate I have ſhewed Man went <hi>out of,</hi> and degenerated <hi>from,</hi> and alſo have opened the direction <hi>unto</hi> the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of <hi>Redemption,</hi> from the <hi>fall</hi> and <hi>loſſe,</hi> and <hi>Reſtoration</hi> unto the firſt Similitude of the Holy One, which unites with the <hi>Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Glory;</hi> unto which ſtate it is poſſible (in the Light) for all Mankinde <hi>to attain;</hi> yet, if they <hi>abide not</hi> in the <hi>immutable Power of Perſervation</hi> that created their Souls, but go from the <hi>unchangeable Life</hi> into the <hi>variable conſultation</hi> with <hi>Fleſh</hi> and its <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>ſenſual Wiſdom,</hi> they may return <hi>backwards,</hi> as the <hi>Sea, Locuſt</hi> and <hi>Canker,</hi> and become as the <hi>Swine that was once waſhed,</hi> but lo, <hi>wallows again in the mire;</hi> and the houſe <hi>may be clean ſwept,</hi> yet except there be a Watch ſtill kept <hi>ſeven unclean Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits may enter,</hi> that are <hi>worſe <hi>than the former</hi>
               </hi> which were dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forth; and <hi>a Virgin ſtate may be attained unto,</hi> but unleſs <hi>the Oyl of Wiſdom</hi> in <hi>Watchfulneſs, Diligence,</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> be retained in the Lamp, alwayes burning and giving light to the whole Soul, it may turn into the darkneſs of <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>filthineſs,</hi> and again may become <hi>adulterate</hi> and <hi>degenerate</hi> from the Life of <hi>Incorruption,</hi> and <hi>Immortal Unchangeable Glory,</hi> which is the <hi>Curſed State. <hi>Wiſdom</hi>
               </hi> therefore <hi>ſmites</hi> the <hi>ſtroakes of Death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the head of Preſumption,</hi> and keeps the <hi>Watch</hi> upon the <hi>Watch-Tower of the Light,</hi> which <hi>diſcovereth</hi> the <hi>Approach</hi> of the <hi>Enemy,</hi> and retains the <hi>Fear,</hi> as a ſtrength for <hi>Courage,</hi> and cloathes the Soul with the <hi>humbleneſs</hi> and <hi>contritedneſs of heart;</hi> for with ſuch the Immortal Power dwelleth, in whoſe <hi>immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtrength</hi> the Salvation and Preſervation is witneſſed; ſo in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98353:20"/>
Him the <hi>Redeemed</hi> have the continual enjoyment of a <hi>ſurpaſſing Sweet</hi> and <hi>conſolating Repoſe</hi> and <hi>Reſt:</hi> Firſt, in the knowledge that the Gracious Power (that hath united them unto Himſelf in the Life of Incorruption and Innocency) can never <hi>vary, change,</hi> nor <hi>altar</hi> from his <hi>Grace, Love,</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs;</hi> and next, though a change may be, which cannot be by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable King of Glory, unleſs it be firſt by the <hi>degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Man's <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>mutable mind</hi> from his Power of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, yet the Soul in the <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>watchfulneſs</hi> (out of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and Arrogancy) in the ground of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> comes to grow in ſuch a ſtrength of the power of Hope, Faith and Truſt in the <hi>Immutable Preſerver</hi> of the <hi>Low</hi> and <hi>Humble,</hi> that in the living and ſenſible perſwaſion it comes to utter (through its aſſurance of the immediate Unity) <hi>that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Afflictions, Tryals, Tribulations, Temptations, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, Buffets, Wounds, Tortures, Priſons, Life</hi>
               </hi> nor <hi>Death, Principalities, Powers, Heights, Depths, Things preſent,</hi> nor <hi>Things to come, <hi>ſhall be ever able to ſeparate the Soul from its Life and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, in, and with the Immutable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver and King of Glory in the Joy of his Everlaſting Virtue.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah! who therefore would not run <hi>as a Greyhound in the courſe,</hi> and flow as the <hi>Floods of the Spring-Tyde;</hi> yea, and fly, as the Dove to her Neſt, unto that which <hi>unites with the <hi>Original Fountain</hi>
               </hi> of all <hi>Excellency, Wiſdom, Sweetneſs</hi> and <hi>Joy,</hi> to be ſwallowed up in its <hi>Ocean</hi> for ever? Oh! the <hi>Felicity</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation</hi> in the ſtate of <hi>Redemption!</hi> how can my weakneſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <hi>its Raviſhing Power?</hi> foraſmuch as in the ſtate of <hi>the Souls Reſtoration</hi> unto the <hi>firſt Beauty, Glory</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> with the King of Glory, there is found a Tower of joyous Safety, far exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Safety that the firſt Man had <hi>in his ſtate of Innocency;</hi> knowing, that though he was <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>pure,</hi> yet wanted the knowledge of the <hi>mutability</hi> and <hi>changeableneſs</hi> of his Soul, from the Power that only could preſerve it <hi>in the Immutable Life;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Concupiſence ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely dye;</hi>
               </hi> which was a Lye, by which the <hi>Innocency</hi> was <hi>beguiled</hi> and <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,</hi> to taſte of the fruit of knowledge in his own fleſh, and then in the Loſſe he ſaw not the Recovery, but clouded himſelf more under it, by covering the defiled parts; but whereas the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98353:20"/>
Soul now ſees its <hi>unity</hi> with the <hi>Immutable Glory,</hi> and knows the <hi>changeableneſs</hi> of the Souls of all Men out of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Power,</hi> and comprehends the <hi>Power of Darkneſs,</hi> with its <hi>Works</hi> and <hi>Perdition;</hi> and alſo knows <hi>the Power of <hi>Redemption</hi>
               </hi> from <hi>Curſe, <hi>Reſtoration</hi>
               </hi> to <hi>Bliſſe,</hi> and <hi>Vnion</hi> with the <hi>Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Glory;</hi> I ſay in the knowledge of all this (which Man in his firſt ſtate of Innocency knew not) ſtands <hi>more glorious arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>ſecurely fortified</hi> on the <hi>Watch-Tower</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> in the pure fear, than the <hi>firſt Man</hi> in his ſtate of <hi>Innocency</hi> did: And by how much alſo the <hi>Mercies, Pitties, Compaſſions, Love</hi> and <hi>glorious Wiſdom</hi> of the Creator is now revealed in his work of <hi>Redemption, Reſtoration,</hi> and <hi>uniting the Soul of man again</hi> unto <hi>Himſelf</hi> in the power of <hi>his quickened Spirit,</hi> theſe Walls of the Eternal Love (which the united Souls now enter to <hi>within</hi>) is a <hi>Glory, Fort</hi> and <hi>Fortreſs,</hi> infinitly exceeding that of the firſt Man's ſtate of Bliſſe in Innocency; Yea, I might even ſpeak as a tongue without end, of this matter, and yet never ſpeak enough (of the revelation of the Power appearing in Glory to the Redeemed, Reſtored, and United Souls) how far it ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that of the knowledge of the firſt Man in Bliſſe, who in his ſtate of Innocency, before Tranſgreſſion was, could not know what <hi>Pitty, Compaſſion, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation was,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not then in a condition of the ſervice of ſuch <hi>properties</hi> and <hi>qualities,</hi> that were hid in the Eternal Wiſdom of Glory; who though He was diſhonoured at firſt by Tranſgreſſion, yet ſuch is his infinite Wiſdom, that He gains Himſelf the greater Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour through the Power of his Redeeming Man out of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. Wherefore the <hi>diſcovery</hi> of the face of Glory being now the more <hi>excellent</hi> and <hi>greater,</hi> the Walls and Bulwarks of Love <hi>muſt needs be the ſtronger,</hi> and the Unity <hi>infinitely nearer</hi> and <hi>dearer,</hi> than the tongues of ten thouſand multitudes can ever utter or expreſs; which may be joyfully received, as the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting <hi>Conſolation</hi> of <hi>all Conſolations,</hi> by all the <hi>Innocent Lambs,</hi> who through the Glorious <hi>Redemption</hi> do know their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the <hi>Immutable Power that created them.</hi> Who therefore (thus in brief) can witneſs to every Oppoſer and Gain-ſayer, that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioneth their ſtate and condition, We are <hi>in the Immutable Life and Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98353:21"/>Finally, The knowledge <hi>of Unchanableneſs</hi> only conſiſting <hi>in the Eternal Power,</hi> cuts off the ſtrength of all <hi>Inſults of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach</hi> (by the ſeed of enmity) caſt upon the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed People</hi> that do abide walking in it, becauſe <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two,</hi> or <hi>a few</hi> have turned (from it) <hi>like the Dog to the vomit,</hi> and the <hi>waſhed Swine again to the wallowing in the mire;</hi> which cannot ſtand upon the <hi>Immutable Power</hi> or <hi>Principle of Holineſs;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, if all Souls ſhould turn from it, as it is a manifeſt Light in every Conſcience, yet the Light and Truth changeth not, but is ſtill the ſame in it ſelf, in <hi>Nature, Power, Vertue</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> (which no man can juſtly deny) though <hi>vailed, clouded,</hi> and in <hi>greater meaſure hid</hi> from the <hi>mutable Soul</hi> that is turned <hi>from it;</hi> Nor can Reproach or Infamy <hi>justly ſtand</hi> upon them that abide <hi>in the Unity</hi> with the <hi>Immutable Glory;</hi> becauſe by the Power thereof they are preſerved out of evil walking before all men <hi>innocently,</hi> not giving <hi>any occaſion</hi> but of <hi>good reports,</hi> to fill the mouths of all men: Therefore, if any man ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach me and my Brethren, whilſt we <hi>continue</hi> and <hi>perſevere</hi> in the Life of <hi>Reſtoration, <hi>united</hi>
               </hi> to the <hi>Unchangeable Holineſs,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others, <hi>one</hi> or <hi>two,</hi> or <hi>a few,</hi> are gone out <hi>into the Defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Curſe;</hi> this ſheweth, that he which ſo <hi>reproacheth us,</hi> ſtands <hi>diſunited unto,</hi> and <hi>adulterated from</hi> the <hi>Life</hi> of <hi>his Creator,</hi> (who is the Power of Equity) and entred into the power of the blackneſs of Iniquity; giving <hi>falſe weight</hi> and <hi>falſe meaſure</hi> in the <hi>Ballance</hi> and <hi>Buſhel</hi> of <hi>Enmity,</hi> which is the <hi>Curſed State;</hi> Becauſe his Creator cannot do the like in the Ballance of his Sanctuary, but is righteous to every mans cauſe. So then the <hi>Reproacher</hi> (by his own unrighteous reproach) writes the mark of <hi>Guilt</hi> in his own <hi>Forehead,</hi> and draws the ſentence of <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judgement</hi> upon his <hi>own head,</hi> as a <hi>rebellious ſon of Enmity,</hi> and Deſpiſer of the life of <hi>Integrity.</hi> And thus the Eternal Sun of the Soul, Power, Wiſdom, Holineſs, and King of Glory (in Himſelf, and in all his Redeemed People) ſtands <hi>magnified, honoured glorified, praiſed,</hi> and <hi>renowned</hi> eternally, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
